<root>
<cl na="counter" xid="id_0">11248</cl>
<cl na="ARC" xid="id_10000">
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1">README 1st: Here are all the sub-clips (sub-clips always start with a "_"). Tap on it to see the bullets each sub-clip contains. Once in a sub-clip, tap on a bullet to view it's content. 
Credits go to the American Red Cross and its affiliates at http://www.redcross.org/disaster/disasterguide/standardmsg.html for placing the Standard Messages into the Public Domain. There is NOT ANY affiliation between Calamity Jane Express ® and the American Red Cross and its affiliates.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_2">Pick safe places in each room..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_3">Practice drop, cover, and hold on..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_4">If you are at risk from earthquakes, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_5">Discuss with members of your household the possibility of earthquakes and what to do to stay safe if one occurs. Knowing how to respond will help reduce fear..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_6">Pick "safe places" in each room of your home and your office or school. A safe place could be under a piece of furniture, such as a sturdy table or desk, or against an interior wall away from windows, bookcases, or tall furniture that could fall on you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_7">The shorter the distance to your safe place, the less likely it is that you will be injured by furnishings that become flying debris during the shaking..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_8">Injury statistics show that persons moving as little as 10 feet during an earthquake's shaking are the most likely experience injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_9">Practice drop, cover, and hold on in each safe place. Drop to the floor, take cover under a sturdy piece of furniture, and hold on to a leg of the furniture. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_10">If suitable furniture is not nearby, sit on the floor next to an interior wall and cover your head and neck with your arms..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_11">Responding quickly in an earthquake may help protect you from injury. Practice drop, cover, and hold on at least twice a year..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_12">Keep a flashlight and sturdy shoes by each persons bed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_13">Inform guests, babysitters, and caregivers of earthquake plans. Everyone in your home should know what to do if an earthquake occurs, even if you are not there at the time..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_14">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_15">Secure your homes structure and objects inside and outside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_16">Bolt and brace water heaters and gas appliances to wall studs. If the water heater tips over, the gas line could break, causing a fire hazard, and the water line could rupture..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_17">The water heater may be your best source of drinkable water following an earthquake. Consider having a licensed professional install flexible fittings for gas and .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_18">Bolt bookcases, china cabinets, and other tall furniture to wall studs. Brace or anchor high or top-heavy objects. During an earthquake, these items can fall over, causing damage or injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_19">Hang heavy items, such as pictures and mirrors, away from beds, couches, and anywhere people sleep or sit. Earthquakes can knock things off walls, causing damage or injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_20">Brace overhead light fixtures. During earthquakes, overhead light fixtures may fall, causing damage or injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_21">Install strong latches or bolts on cabinets. The contents of cabinets can shift during the shaking of an earthquake. Latches will prevent cabinets from opening and spilling out the contents. Place large or heavy objects on shelves near the floor..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_22">Secure large items that might fall and break (televisions, computers, etc.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_23">Store weed killers, pesticides, and flammable products securely in closed, latched metal cabinets..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_24">Evaluate animal facilities and places your pets like to hide in, to ensure that any hazardous substances or structures are as safe as possible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_25">Consider having your building evaluated by a professional structural design .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_26">What to Do During an Earthquake.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_27">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_28">If inside when the shaking starts, move no more than a few steps and drop,cover, and hold on..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_29">If outside, find a clear spot and drop..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_30">If you are inside when the shaking starts, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_31">Drop, cover, and hold on. Move only a few steps to a nearby safe place. Most people injured in earthquakes move more than ten feet during the shaking..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_32">If you are elderly or have a mobility impairment, remain where you are, bracing yourself in place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_33">If you are in bed, stay there, hold on, and protect your head with a pillow. You are less likely to be injured if you stay in bed. Broken glass on the floor can injure you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_34">Stay away from windows. Windows can shatter with such force that you can be injured by flying glass even if you are several feet away..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_35">Stay indoors until the shaking stops and you are sure it is safe to exit. In buildings in the United States, you are safer if you stay where you are until the shaking stops. a.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_36">If you go outside, move quickly away from the building to prevent injury from falling debris..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_37">Be aware that fire alarm and sprinkler systems frequently go off in buildings during an earthquake, even if there is no fire. Check for and extinguish small fires, and exit via the stairs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_38">If you are in a coastal area, drop, cover, and hold on during an earthquake and then move immediately to higher ground when the shaking stops. Tsunamis (large ocean waves) are often generated by earthquakes. (See Tsunamis.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_39">If you are outdoors when the shaking starts, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_40">Find a clear spot away from buildings, trees, streetlights, and power lines..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_41">Drop to the ground and stay there until the shaking stops. Injuries can occur from falling trees, streetlights, power lines, and building debris..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_42">If you are in a vehicle, pull over to a clear location, stop, and stay there with your seatbelt fastened until the shaking stops. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_43">Trees, power lines, poles, street signs, overpasses, and other overhead items may fall during earthquakes. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_44">Stopping in a clear location will reduce your risk, and a hard-topped vehicle will help protect you from flying or falling objects. Once the shaking has stopped, proceed with caution. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_45">Avoid bridges or ramps that might have been damaged by the quake..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_46">If you are in a mountainous area or near unstable slopes or cliffs, be alert for falling rocks and other debris that could be loosened by the earthquake. Landslides are often triggered by earthquakes. (See Landslides.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_47">What to Do After an Earthquake.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_48">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_49">Expect aftershocks..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_50">Check yourself and then others..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_51">Look for fires..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_52">When the shaking stops, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_53">Expect aftershocks. Each time you feel one, drop, cover, and hold on. Aftershocks frequently occur minutes, days, weeks, and even months following an earthquake..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_54">Check yourself for injuries and get first aid if necessary before helping injured or trapped persons..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_55">Put on long pants, a long-sleeved shirt, sturdy shoes, and work gloves to protect yourself from injury by broken objects..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_56">Look quickly for damage in and around your home and get everyone out if your home is unsafe. Aftershocks following earthquakes can cause further damage to unstable buildings..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_57">If your home has experienced damage, get out before aftershocks happen. Use the stairs, not an elevator..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_58">Listen to a portable, battery-operated radio or television for updated emergency information and instructions. If the electricity is out, this may be your main source of information..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_59">Local radio and television stations and local officials will provide the most appropriate advice for your particular situation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_60">Check the telephones in your home or workplace. If a phone was knocked off its cradle during the shaking of the earthquake, hang it up. Allow 10 seconds or more for the line to reset..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_61">If the phone lines are undamaged, you should get a dial tone. Use a telephone or cell phone only to make a brief call to your Family Disaster Plan contact and to report life-threatening emergencies..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_62">Telephone lines and cellular equipment are frequently overwhelmed in disaster situations and need to be clear for emergency calls to get through..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_63">Cellular telephone equipment is subject to damage by quakes and cell phones may not be able to get a signal, but regular land line phones may work..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_64">Look for and extinguish small fires. Fire is the most common hazard following earthquakes. Fires followed the San Francisco earthquake of 1906 for three days, creating more damage than the earthquake..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_65">Clean up spilled medications, bleach, gasoline, or other flammable liquids immediately. Avoid the hazard of a chemical emergency..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_66">Open closet and cabinet doors cautiously. Contents may have shifted during the shaking and could fall, creating further damage or injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_67">Help people who require special assistance infants, elderly people, those without transportation, large families who may need additional help in an emergency situation, people with disabilities, and the people who care for them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_68">Watch out for fallen power lines or broken gas lines, and stay out of damaged areas. Hazards caused by earthquakes are often difficult to see, and you could be easily injured..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_69">Watch animals closely. Keep all your animals under your direct control. Pets may become disoriented, particularly if the disaster has affected scent markers that normally allow them to find their home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_70">Pets may be able to escape from your house, and fencing may be broken. Be aware of hazards at nose and paw level, particularly debris, spilled chemicals, fertilizers, and other substances that might seem to be dangerous to humans..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_71">In addition, the behavior of pets may change dramatically after an earthquake, becoming aggressive or defensive, so be aware of their well-being and take measures to protect them from hazards, including displaced wild animals, and to ensure the safety....;.;.;... of other people and animals..;;</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_72">Stay out of damaged buildings. Damaged buildings may be destroyed by after following the main quake..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_73">If you were away from home, return only when authorities say it is safe. When you return home:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_74">Be alert for and observe official warnings..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_75">Use extreme caution. Check for damages outside your home. Then, if the structure appears safe to enter, check for damages inside. Building damage may have occurred where you least expect it..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_76">Carefully watch every step you take. Get out of the building if you think it is in danger of collapsing. Do not smoke; smoking in confined areas can cause fires..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_77">Examine walls, floors, doors, staircases, and windows. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_78">Check for gas leaks. If you smell gas or hear a blowing or hissing noise, open a window and get everyone out quickly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_79">Turn off the gas, using the outside main valve if you can, and call the gas company from a neighbor's home. If you turn off the gas for any reason, it must be turned back on by a professional.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_80">Look for damage to the electrical system. If you see sparks or broken or frayed wires, or if you smell burning insulation, turn off the electricity at the main fuse box or circuit breaker..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_81">If you have to step in water to get to the fuse box or circuit breaker, call an electrician first for advice..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_82">Check for damage to sewage and water lines. If you suspect sewage lines are damaged, avoid using the toilets and call a plumber. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_83">If water pipes are damaged, contact the water company and avoid using water from the tap. You can obtain safe water from undamaged water heaters or by melting ice cubes. (See Appendix: Drinking Water Safety.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_84">Watch for loose plaster, drywall, and ceilings that could fall..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_85">Thunderstorms.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_86">Watch, Warning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_87">A Severe Thunderstorm WATCH means severe thunderstorms are possible in and near thewatch area. People in a watch area should keep informed and be ready to act if a severethunderstorm warning is issued..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_88">A Severe thunderstorm WARNING means severe weather has been reported by spottersor indicated by radar. Warnings indicate imminent danger to life and property..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_89">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_90">Determine your risk..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_91">Prepare members of your household..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_92">Pick a safe place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_93">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_94">Discuss thunderstorm safety with members of your household. Be aware that a thunderstorm could produce a tornado. Tornadoes develop from severe thunderstorms along and ahead of cold fronts..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_95">Pick a safe place in your home for household members to gather during at thunderstorm. This should be a place where there are no windows, skylights, or glassdoors, which could be broken by strong winds or hail and cause damage or injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_96">In preparation for possible tornado warnings, consider making your severe thunderstorm safe place on the lowest floor of the building..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_97">Learn how to crouch low to the ground on the balls of your feet. Place your hands on your knees and your head between your knees. Minimize your body's surface area, and minimize your contact with the ground..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_98">Lightning current often enters a victim through the ground rather than by a direct overhead strike..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_99">Protect Your Property.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_100">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_101">Actively prepare your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_102">Check your insurance coverage..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_103">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_104">Make a list of items to bring inside in the event of a severe thunderstorm. Having a list will help you remember things that may be broken or blown away in strong winds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_105">Keep trees and shrubbery trimmed. Make trees more wind resistant by removing diseased or damaged limbs, then strategically remove branches so that wind can blowthrough. Strong winds frequently break weak limbs and hurl them at great speed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_106">Remove any debris or loose items from around your home and out buildings and from pastures. Branches and firewood may become missiles in strong winds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_107">Protect your animals. Ensure that any outbuildings, pastures, or corrals that house animals are protected in the same way as your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_108">When installing or changing fencelines, consider placing them in such a way that your animals are able to move to higherground in the event of flooding..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_109">Consider installing permanent shutters to cover windows. Shutters can be closed quickly and provide the safest protection for windows..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_110">animals. Lightning rods will carry the electrical charge of lightning bolts safely to the ground, greatly reducing the chance of a lightning-induced fire..; 5 ?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_111">What to Do Before a Severe Thunderstorm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_112">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_113">Stay informed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_114">Prepare to shelter..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_115">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_116">Use a NOAA Weather Radio to keep you informed of watches and warnings issuedin your area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_117">If planning a trip or extended period of time outdoors, be aware of the weather forecast. Knowing what the weather could be will help you be prepared to respond if necessary..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_118">Having a raincoat, umbrella, and disaster supplies kit available will make it easier to deal with severe weather if it occurs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_119">Postpone outdoor activities if thunderstorms are imminent. Coaches of outdoor sports teams should use a NOAA Weather Radio during practice sessions and games..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_120">Threatening weather can endanger athletes, staff, and spectators. Remember that many people struck by lightning are not in an area where rain is falling. Postponing activities is your best way to avoid being caught in a dangerous situation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_121">Keep an eye on the sky. Pay attention to weather clues around you that may warn of imminent danger. Look for darkening skies, flashes of lightning, or increasing wind,which may be signs of an approaching thunderstorm..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_122">Be aware of your surroundings. Look for places you could go if severe weather threatens..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_123">Listen for the sound of thunder. If you can hear thunder, you are close enough to the storm to be struck by lightning. Go to safe shelter immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_124">Even if there is no official thunderstorm warning, if you see signs of a thunderstorm, take precautions..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_125">What to Do During a Severe Thunderstorm Watch.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_126">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_127">Keep informed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_128">Prepare to shelter..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_129">Avoid lightning attractors..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_130">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_131">Avoid natural lightning rods, such as golf clubs, fishing poles, tractors, bicycles,and camping equipment. Lightning is attracted to metal and poles or rods..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_132">Be prepared to take shelter. A sturdy building is the safest place to be during a severe thunderstorm. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_133">Avoid gazebos, rain or picnic shelters, golf carts, baseball dugouts, bleachers, and other isolated structures in otherwise open areas because such places are often struck by lightning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_134">In addition, gazebos and picnic shelters are often poorly anchored and subject to being uprooted and blown around in strong thunderstorm winds. They also offer little protection from large hail..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_135">If you perceive that a severe thunderstorm is approaching:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_136">Secure outdoor objects such as lawn furniture that could blow away orcause damage or injury. Take lightweight objects inside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_137">Bring your companion animals indoors and maintain direct control of them. Be sure that your pet disaster kit is ready to go..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_138">If possible, bring horses and livestock into your barn. Do not allow horses or livestock to gather under an isolated tree or otherwise present a risk from a lightning strike..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_139">Shutter windows and close outside doors securely. This will help protect your home from damaging winds or flying debris..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_140">Avoid electrical equipment and telephones. Lightning could follow the wire. Television sets are particularly dangerous at this time. Use a battery-powered radio or television..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_141">Avoid bathtubs, water faucets, and sinks because metal pipes can transmit electricity..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_142">What to Do During a Severe Thunderstorm Warning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_143">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_144">Stay informed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_145">Go to shelter..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_146">Avoid lightning attractors..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_147">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_148">Draw the blinds and shades over windows. If windows break because objects are blown by the wind or large hail, the shades will help prevent glass from shattering into your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_149">Unplug appliances and avoid using the telephone or any electrical appliances. If lightning strikes, telephone lines and metal pipes can conduct electricity. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_150">Leaving electric lights on, however, does not increase the chances of your home being struck by lightning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_151">Avoid taking a bath or shower, or running water for any other purpose. Metal pipes and plumbing can conduct electricity if struck by lightning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_152">Turn off the air conditioner. Power surges from lightning can overload the compressor,resulting in a costly repair job..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_153">Maintain direct control of your animals. Many animals are unsettled by thunderstorms and it is more comforting and safe for them to be with you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_154">What to Do if You Are Outside and a Severe Thunderstorm Is Approaching.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_155">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_156">Get to shelter..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_157">Avoid likely lightning targets..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_158">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_159">Find shelter immediately. If you are boating or swimming, get to land, get off the beach, and find shelter immediately. Stay away from rivers, lakes, and other bodies of water. Water is an excellent conductor of electricity..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_160">When lightning strikes nearby, the electrical charge can travel through the water. Each year, people are killed by nearby lightning strikes while in or on the water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_161">Take shelter in a substantial, permanent, enclosed structure, such as a reinforced building. A sturdy building is the safest place to be..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_162">Avoid gazebos, rain or picnic shelters, golf carts, baseball dugouts, bleachers, and other isolated structures inotherwise open areas because such places are often struck by lightning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_163">In addition, gazebos and picnic shelters are often poorly anchored and subject to being uprooted and blown around in strong thunderstorm winds. They also offer little protection from large hail..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_164">If there is no reinforced building in sight, take shelter in a vehicle. Keep the windows closed and avoid convertibles. Rubber-soled shoes and rubber tires provide no protection from lightning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_165">However, the steel frame of a hard-topped vehicle provides increased protection if you are not touching metal. Although you may be injured if lightning strikes your vehicle, you are much safer inside a vehicle than outside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_166">If you are in the woods, find an area protected by a low clump of trees. Never standbeneath a single large tree in the open. Be aware of the potential for flooding in low-lyingareas..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_167">As a last resort and if no suitable structure or vehicle is available, go to a low lying,open place away from trees, poles, or metal objects. Make sure the place you pick is not subject to flooding..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_168">Crouch low to the ground on the balls of your feet. Place your hands on your knees and your head between your knees. Minimize your body's surface area, and minimize your contact with the ground..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_169">Lightning current often enters a victim through the ground rather than by a direct overhead strike..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_170">Avoid tall structures, such as towers, tall trees, fences, telephone lines, and powerlines. Lightning strikes the tallest objects in an area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_171">Stay away from natural lightning rods, such as golf clubs, tractors, fishing rods, bicycles, and camping equipment. Lightning is attracted to metal and poles or rods..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_172">If you are isolated in a level field or prairie and you feel your hair stand on end (which indicates that lightning is about to strike), crouch low to the ground on the balls of your feet. Place your hands on your knees and your head between your knees. Minimize your body's surface area, and minimize your contact with the ground. Lightning current often enters a victim through the ground rather than by a direct overhead strike..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_173">What to Do If You Are Driving During a Severe Thunderstorm or Heavy Rain.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_174">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_175">Pull over..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_176">Stay in the vehicle..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_177">Be alert for flooding.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_178">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_179">Pull safely onto the shoulder of the road and stop, making sure you are away from any trees or other tall objects that could fall on the vehicle..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_180">Stay in the vehicle and turn on the emergency flashers until the heavy rain subsides. Heavy rain produced by thunderstorms can greatly reduce visibility..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_181">Emergency flashers will alert other drivers that you have stopped. Keep the windows closed. You are safer from lightning in a vehicle than out in the open..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_182">Avoid contact with metal or other conducting surfaces outside or inside thevehicle. Lightning that strikes nearby can travel through wet ground to your vehicle. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_183">The steel frame of a hard-topped vehicle provides increased protection if you are not touching metal. Rubber tires provide no protection from lightning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_184">Avoid contact with potential conductors to reduce your chance of being shocked. Although you may be injured if lightning strikes your vehicle, you are much safer inside than outside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_185">Avoid flooded roads. Many flood fatalities are caused by people attempting to drive through water or people playing in high water. The depth of water is not always obvious.The roadbed may be washed out under the water, and you could be stranded or trapped.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_186">Rapidly rising water may stall the engine, engulf the vehicle and its occupants,and sweep them away. Look out for flooding at highway dips, bridges, and low areas..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_187">As little as six inches of water may cause you to lose control of your vehicle and two feet (0.6 meter) of flowing water will carry away most automobiles, including SUVs and pickup trucks..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_188">What to Do After a Severe Thunderstorm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_189">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_190">Stay informed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_191">Be alert to hazards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_192">Help others..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_193">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_194">Help people who require special assistance infants, elderly people, those without transportation, large families who may need additional help in an emergency situation, people with disabilities, and the people who care for them.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_195">Stay away from storm-damaged areas to avoid putting yourself at further risk from the residual effects of severe thunderstorms. Sightseers cause additional problems and hamper local responders assisting those in need..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_196">If assistance is needed in your area and telephone communications are disrupted, go to your nearest fire or police station to request assistance..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_197">Watch animals closely. Keep all your animals under your direct control. Pets may become disoriented before, during, and after severe thunderstorms. If there has been wind damage, pets may be able to escape from your home or your fence may be broken..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_198">Be aware of hazards at nose and paw or hoof level, particularly debris, downed powerlines things that can be dangerous to humans..; 5 50 ? 59</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_199">In addition, the behavior of pets may change dramatically after a severe storm, becoming aggressive or defensive, so be aware of their well-being and take measures to protect them from hazards, including displaced wild animals, and to ensure the safety of other people and animals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_200">What to Do if Someone Is Struck by Lightning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_201">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_202">Get help..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_203">Give first aid..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_204">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_205">Call for help. Get someone to dial 9-1-1 or your local emergency number. Medical attention is needed as quickly as possible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_206">Give first aid. If the person has stopped breathing, begin rescue breathing. If the person s heart has stopped beating, a trained person should give CPR. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_207">If the person has a pulse and is breathing, look for other possible injuries and care for them if necessary..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_208">Check the person for burns in two places. The injured person has received an electrical shock and may be burned both where the current entered and where it exited his or her body..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_209">Being struck by lightning can also cause nervous system damage, broken bones, and loss of hearing or eyesight. People struck by lightning carry no electrical charge that can shock other people, and they can be handled safely..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_210">Hurricanes.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_211">Watch, Warning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_212">A Hurricane/Tropical Storm WATCH means there is a threat of hurricane/tropicalstorm conditions within 36 hours..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_213">People in a watch area should review their hurricane plans (Family Disaster Plan, Disaster Supplies Kit, evacuation routes), keepinformed, and be ready to act if a warning is issued..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_214">A Hurricane/Tropical Storm WARNING means hurricane/tropical storm conditionsare expected in 24 hours or less..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_215">When a warning is issued, people should complete their storm preparations and leave the threatened area if directed to do so by localofficials..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_216">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_217">Determine your risk.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_218">Consider flood insurance.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_219">Make an evacuation plan..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_220">Prepare members of your household..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_221">If you are at risk from hurricanes, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_222">Determine where to move your boat in an emergency. Marinas and other storage facilities may fill up quickly. Some locations may have less risk of damage than others.You may be required to secure your boat well in advance of an approaching hurricane..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_223">Protect your animals. Ensure that any outbuildings, pastures, or corrals that houseanimals are protected in the same way as your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_224">When installing or changing fencelines, consider placing them in such a way that your animals are able to move to higher water in the event of flooding. Get rid of debris around your home and any outbuildings as well as in pastures..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_225">Know where to go with your animals. Because evacuation shelters generally do not accept pets, except for service animals, you must plan ahead to ensure that your family and pets will have a safe place to stay..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_226">Do this research well before disaster strikes. See chapter on Evacuation and Sheltering, and Post-disaster Safety for more information on planning for evacuating your animals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_227">Protect Your Property.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_228">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_229">Keep an in case of hurricane to-dolist..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_230">Get proper protection for all windows and doors..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_231">If you are at risk from hurricanes, well before a hurricane threatens, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_232">Make a list of items to bring inside in the event of a storm. A list will help you remember anything that can be broken or picked up by strong winds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_233">Install permanent hurricane shutters if possible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_234">If you do not have hurricane shutters, buy the plywood and other items needed toboard up windows and doors. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_235">Get half-inch outdoor plywood marine plywood is best. Cut it to fit the outside frame of each window and door and drill the holes and install the anchors for the screws. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_236">Do not tape windows. Taping does not prevent windows from breaking and takes critical time from more effective preparedness measures..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_237">Remove any debris or loose items in your yard. Hurricane winds, often in excess of 100 miles (161 kilometers) per hour, can turn unanchored items into deadly missiles..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_238">Keep trees and shrubbery trimmed. Make trees more wind resistant by removing diseased or damaged limbs, then strategically remove branches so that wind can blow through..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_239">Hurricane winds frequently break weak limbs and hurl them at great speed, damaging whatever they hit. Debris collection services may not be operating just before a storm, so it is best to do this well in advance of an approaching storm..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_240">Fix loose rain gutters and downspouts and clear them if they are clogged. Hurricanes often bring long periods of heavy rain. Cleaning and securing drainage systems will help protect your home from water damage..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_241">Strengthen garage doors. Hurricane winds can enter through a damaged garage door,lift the roof, and destroy the home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_242">If you live in a floodplain or area prone to flooding, follow flood preparedness precautions. Tropical cyclones can bring great amounts of rain and frequently causefloods. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_243">Some hurricanes have dropped more than 10 inches (25 centimeters) of rain injust a few hours.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_244">Take similar measures to protect your animals. Make sure that you strengthen and protect any outbuildings that may house animals in the same way you protect your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_245">Explore sheltering options for your pets. Contact relatives, friends, hotels and motels,and other facilities to make a definite plan for sheltering your animals. Many communitiesare developing emergency animal shelters similar to shelters for people..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_246">Contact your local emergency management agency to find out about emergency animal shelters in your community, in the event that you have nowhere else to go and need to go to public shelterwith your animals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_247">Include your pets in your evacuation and sheltering drills. Practice evacuating yourpets so they will get used to entering and traveling calmly in their carriers..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_248">If you haveh horses or other large animals, be sure that they are accustomed to entering a trailer. Practice bringing your pets indoors, into your safe room, so that if you are required to shelter in place, they will be comfortable..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_249">What to Do During a Hurricane/Tropical Storm Watch.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_250">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_251">Listen to and watch local news..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_252">Prepare your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_253">Evacuate if advised by authorities..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_254">Avoid floodwater.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_255">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_256">Heed the advice of local officials, and evacuate if they advise it. (See Appendix:What to Do if Evacuation Is Necessary Because of a Storm.) Following their advice isyour best protection..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_257">Avoid flooded roads and watch for washed-out bridges. Local officials may close certain roads, especially near the coast, when effects of the hurricanereach the coast..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_258">Prepare your property for high winds. Hurricane winds can lift large, heavy objects and send them crashing into homes. Anything not secured may become a deadly or damaging projectile..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_259">Bring lawn furniture inside, as well as outdoor decorations or ornaments, trash cans, hanging plants, or anything else that can be picked up by the wind..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_260">Secure your home by closing the windows and doors and then closing the hurricane shutters. If you do not have hurricane shutters, close and board up all windows anddoors..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_261">If possible and if it can be safely done, remove outside antennas.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_262">Moor a boat securely or move it to a designated safe place. Use rope or chain to secure a boat to a trailer. Use tie-downs to anchor a trailer to the ground or to abuilding..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_263">Fill your car's gas tank. If advised to evacuate, you may have to travel a long distance or you may be stuck in traffic for a long time. Gas stations along the route may be closed.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_264">Stock up on prescription medications. Stores and pharmacies may be closed after the storm..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_265">If you are in a mobile home, check the tie-downs. Mobile homes may be less affected by strong winds if they are tied down according to the manufacturer's instructions.Properly tied-down homes are more likely to stay fixed to their foundations..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_266">Check your Disaster Supplies Kit. Some supplies may need to be replaced or restocked..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_267">Turn the refrigerator and freezer to the coldest setting. Open them only when absolutely necessary, then close them quickly. Keeping the coldest air in will help perishables last much longer in the event of a power failure..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_268">Store valuables and personal papers in a safe-deposit box or in a waterproof container on the highest level of your home. Hurricanes can cause much water damage inside homes. Protecting valuables in this manner will provide the best security..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_269">Turn off utilities if told to do so by authorities. Authorities may ask you to turn off water or electric utilities to prevent damage to your home or within the community..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_270">Most of the time they will tell you to leave the gas on because, if you shut if off, a professional is required to turn your gas back on, and it may be several weeks before you receive service..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_271">Turn off propane tanks. Propane tanks may be damaged or dislodged by strong winds or water. Turning them off reduces the fire potential..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_272">Unplug small appliances. Small appliances may be affected by electrical power surges that may occur as the storm approaches. Unplugging them reduces potential damage..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_273">Review your evacuation plan. Make sure your planned route is the same as the currently recommended route. Sometimes roads may be closed or blocked, requiring a different route..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_274">Stay away from floodwater. If you come upon a flooded road, turn around and go another way. Most hurricane-related deaths are caused by floods from heavy rainfall..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_275">The National Hurricane Center reports that more then one-third of inland flooding deaths involve people trapped in cars while trying to escape rising water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_276">The depth of water is not always obvious. The roadbed may be washed out under the water, and you could be stranded or trapped. Rapidly rising water may stall the engine, engulf the vehicle and its occupants, and sweep them away..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_277">As little as six inches of water may cause you to lose control of your vehicle and two feet (0.6 meter) of water will carry away most automobiles, SUVs, and pickup trucks..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_278">Consider a precautionary evacuation of large or numerous animals. If you think an evacuation might be advised or ordered and if you have large, unusual, or numerous animals, start evacuating them as soon as you are aware of impending danger..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_279">If you are using a horse or other trailer to evacuate your animals, move early rather than wait until it may be too late to maneuver a trailer through slow traffic. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_280">The winds or water may be too high, or other hazards may make this too dangerous for you and for them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_281">What to Do During a Hurricane/Tropical Storm Warning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_282">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_283">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_284">Evacuate if advised by authorities, or stay inside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_285">If in a mobile home, evacuate immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_286">Avoid floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_287">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_288">If officials advise you to leave your home, go as soon as possible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_289">Take your Disaster Supplies Kit and go to a shelter or to the out-of-town contact identified in your Family Disaster Plan. Call your contact and tell him or her when you are leaving and where you are going..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_290">Local officials will advise you to evacuate only if they conclude that you are in danger. It is important to follow their instructions as soon as possible. Roads may become blockedand the storm can worsen, preventing safe escape..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_291">If you evacuate, take your pets with you. If it is not safe for you, it is not safe for them.Be sure to take your pet disaster kit with you. Leaving them will endanger not only your pets, but also yourself and emergency responders..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_292">If you are not advised to evacuate, stay indoors, away from windows, skylights, and doors, even if they are covered. Stay on the floor least likely to be affected by strong winds and floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_293">A small interior room without windows on the first floor isusually the safest place. Have as many walls between you and the outside winds as possible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_294">Sometimes strong winds and projectiles may tear hurricane shutters off, so stay away from windows even if they are covered. Lie on the floor under a table or other sturdy object. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_295">Being under a sturdy object will offer greater protection from falling objects..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_296">Close all interior doors. Secure external doors. Closed doors will help prevent damaging hurricane winds from entering rooms..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_297">Have a supply of flashlights and extra batteries handy. Flashlights provide the safest emergency lighting source. DO NOT USE CANDLES. Do not use kerosene lamps, which require a great deal of ventilation and are not designed for indoor use..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_298">Store drinking water in clean plastic bottles and cooking utensils. Public water supplies and wells may become contaminated, or electric pumps may be in operative if power is lost. Often, a persons greatest need following a disaster is water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_299">Fill bathtubs and sinks with water to use for flushing the toilet and washing floors andclothing. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_300">Do not use water that has been stored in glazed tubs or sinks for drinking or to bathe young children because over time lead can leach from the glaze into the water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_301">If power is lost, turn off major appliances to reduce the power surge when electricity is restored. When electricity is restored, the surge from many major appliances starting at the same time may cause damage or destroy the appliances..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_302">Turning off or unplugging major appliances will allow you to decide when it is best to turn them back on..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_303">If you are in a mobile home, recheck the tie-downs and evacuate immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_304">Be aware that the calm "eye" is deceptive; the storm is not over. Once the eyepasses over your area, the winds increase and blow from the opposite direction..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_305">Trees,shrubs, buildings, and other objects damaged by the first winds can be broken or destroyed by the second winds. The opposing winds begin suddenly and have surprised and injured many people who ventured out during the eye..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_306">Watch out for flooding. Hurricanes and tropical storms often drop large amounts of rain and cause severe flooding, even when they are weakening or are no longer a named storm. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_307">"Weak" tropical storms are just as capable of producing heavy rain and flooding as major hurricanes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_308">Be alert for tornadoes. Tornadoes can happen during a hurricane. If a tornado occurs in connection with a hurricane, remain indoors on a lower level, in the center of your home, in a closet or bathroom without windows..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_309">Bring your companion animals indoors and maintain direct control of them. Besure that your pet disaster kit is ready to go, along with your family disaster kit, should you need to evacuate..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_310">If the storm is predicted to be not very strong and if pastured animals have access to high ground, it is better to let them out into their pastures than to leave them in a barn, unless that barn is very well constructed and protected..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_311">Horses and cattle are able to avoid windborne debris if they have enough area to move. In the last hours before a hurricane or tropical storm hits, it may be safer to do this than to attempt a last-minute evacuation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_312">What to Do After a Hurricane/Tropical Storm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_313">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_314">Listen to and watch the news..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_315">Watch for floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_316">Check for dangers inside and outside.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_317">After a hurricane is over, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_318">If you evacuated, return home when local officials tell you it is safe. Local officials on the scene are your best source of information about accessible areas and passable roads..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_319">Stay alert for extended rainfall and subsequent flooding, even after the hurricane or tropical storm has weakened. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_320">Hurricanes may stall or change direction when they make landfall, or they may bring a lot of rain upriver, causing additional flood hazards for hours or days after the storm..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_321">Stay away from floodwater. Drive only if absolutely necessary and avoid flooded roadsand washed-out bridges. Continue to follow all flood safety messages. Floodwaters may last for days following a hurricane..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_322">If you come upon a flooded road, turn around and go another way. Never try to walk, swim, or drive through swiftly moving water. Many flood fatalities are caused by people attempting to drive through water or people playing in highwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_323">If it is moving swiftly, even water six inches (15 centimeters) deep can sweep you off your feet, and two feet (0.6 meter) can carry away most vehicles. Also, standing water may be electrically charged from underground or downed power lines..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_324">If you come upon a barricade, follow detour signs or turn around and go another way. Barricades are put up by local officials to protect people from unsafe roads. Driving beyond them can be a serious risk..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_325">Help injured or trapped persons. Give first aid where appropriate. Do not move seriously injured persons unless they are in immediate danger of further injury. Call for help..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_326">Help people who require special assistance infants, elderly people, those without transportation, large families who may need additional help in an emergency situation, people with disabilities, and the people who care for them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_327">If someone needs to be rescued, call professionals with the right equipment to help. Many people have been killed or injured trying to rescue others in flooded areas..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_328">Stay away from damaged areas. Your presence might hamper rescue and other emergency operations, and put you at further risk from the residual effects of floods, such as contaminated water, crumbled roads, landslides, mudflows, and other hazards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_329">Stay away from damaged areas. Your presence might hamper rescue and other emergency operations, and put you at further risk from the residual effects of floods, such as contaminated water, crumbled roads, landslides, mudflows, and other hazards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_330">Stay out of any building that has water around it. Floodwater often undermines foundations, causing buildings to sink, floors to crack, or walls to collapse..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_331">Wear long pants, a long-sleeved shirt, and sturdy shoes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_332">Use battery-powered lanterns or flashlights when examining buildings. DO NOT USE CANDLES..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_333">Examine walls, floors, doors, staircases, and windows to make sure that the building is not in danger of collapsing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_334">Look for fire hazards. There may be broken or leaking gas lines, flooded electrical circuits, or submerged furnaces or electrical appliances..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_335">Check for gas leaks. If you smell gas or hear a blowing or hissing noise, open a windowand get everyone outside quickly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_336">Turn off the gas, using the outside main valve if you can, and call the gas company from a neighbor's home. If you turn off the gas for any reason, it must be turned back on by a professional..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_337">Look for electrical system damage. If you see sparks or broken or frayed wires, or if you smell burning insulation, turn off the electricity at the main fuse box or circuit breaker..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_338">If you have to step in water to get to the fuse box or circuit breaker, call an electrician first for advice. Electrical equipment should be checked and dried before being returned to service..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_339">Check for sewage and water line damage. If you suspect sewage lines are damaged, avoid using the toilets and call a plumber. If water pipes are damaged, contact the watercompany, and avoid using water from the tap..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_340">You can obtain safe water from undamaged water heaters or by melting ice cubes made before the hurricane struck. Turn off the main water valve before using water from these sources..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_341">Avoid drinking or preparing food with tap water until you are certain it is not contaminated. Hurricane-driven floodwater may have contaminated public water supplies or wells..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_342">Local officials should advise you on the safety of the drinking water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_343">Check refrigerated food for spoilage. (See Appendix: Keeping Refrigerated Food Safe if the Power Goes Out.) If power was lost, some foods may be spoiled. If in doubt, throw it out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_344">Watch out for animals, especially poisonous snakes, that may have come into buildings with the floodwater. Use a stick to poke through debris. Floodwater flushes many animals and snakes out of their homes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_345">Watch for loose plaster, drywall, and ceilings that could fall..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_346">Take pictures of the damage, both of the building and its contents, for insurance claims..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_347">Open windows and doors to ventilate and dry your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_348">Pump out flooded basements gradually (about one-third of the water per day) toavoid structural damage. If the water is pumped out completely in a short period oftime, pressure from water on the outside could cause basement walls to collapse..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_349">Service damaged septic tanks, cesspools, pits, and leaching systems as soon as possible. Damaged sewage systems are health hazards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_350">Use the telephone only for emergency calls. Telephone lines are frequently overwhelmed in disaster situations. They need to be clear for emergency calls to get through..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_351">Watch animals closely. Keep all your animals under your direct control. Pets may become disoriented, particularly if the disaster has affected scent markers that normally allow them to find their home.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_352">Pets may be able to escape from your home or your fence may be broken. Be aware of hazards at nose and paw or hoof level, particularly debris, spilled chemicals, fertilizers, and other substances that might not seem to be dangerous to humans..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_353">In addition, the behavior of pets may change dramatically after a disaster, becoming aggressive or defensive, so be aware of their well-being and take measures to protect them from hazards, including displaced wild animals....;.;.;...and to ensure the safety of other people and animals..;;</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_354">Tornadoes.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_355">Watch, Warning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_356">A Tornado WATCH means that tornadoes are possible in and near the watch area. People in a watch area should review their tornado plans (Family Disaster Plan,Disaster Supplies Kit, tornado safe room), and be ready to act if a warning is issuedor they suspect a tornado is approaching..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_357">A Tornado WARNING means that a tornado has been sighted or indicated byweather radar. Tornado warnings indicate imminent danger to life and property.People in a warning area should go immediately to their safe room..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_358">If they are in a vehicle, they should get out of the vehicle and go to shelter in a nearby sturdy building or lie flat in a low spot away from the vehicle..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_359">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_360">Prepare members of your household..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_361">Pick a tornado safe place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_362">Know your community s warning system..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_363">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_364">Pick a safe place in your home where family members, including pets, could gather during a tornado. The safest place to be is underground, or as low to the ground as possible, and away from all windows..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_365">If you have a basement or storm cellar, make it your safe place. If you do not have a basement or storm cellar, consider an interior bathroom, closet, or hallway on thelowest floor..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_366">Putting as many walls as you can between you and the outside will provide additional protection. Less than two percent of all tornadoes have winds over 205 miles (330kilometers) per hour and are powerful enough to completely destroy a sturdy building.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_367">Make sure there are no windows or glass doors in your safe place and keep this place uncluttered..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_368">Consider having your tornado safe place reinforced. (See Appendix: Wind Safe Room.) Additional reinforcement will add more protection from the damaging effects of tornado winds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_369">If you are in a high-rise building, pick a place in a hallway in the center of the building. You may not have enough time to go to the lowest floor. Center hallways are often the mos tstructurally reinforced part of a building..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_370">If you live in a mobile home, choose a safe place in a nearby sturdy building. A sturdy building provides greater protection. If your mobile home park has a designated shelter, make it your safe place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_371">Conduct periodic tornado drills, so everyone remembers what to do if a tornado approaches. Practice having everyone in the household go to your designated safe place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_372">Have everyone get under a sturdy piece of furniture, hold on with one hand, and protect his orher head and neck with the other. Practicing your plan makes the appropriate response more of a reaction, requiring less thinking time during an actual emergency.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_373">Check at your workplace and your children's schools and day care centers to learn about their tornado emergency plans. Every building has different safe places. It is important to know where they are and how to get there in an emergency..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_374">Discuss tornadoes with your family. Everyone should know what to do in case all family members are not together. Discussing disaster preparedness ahead of time helps reduce fearand lets everyone know what to do in a tornado situation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_375">Protect Your Property.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_376">CORE ACTION MESSAGE.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_377">Prepare your home and property..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_378">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_379">Make a list of items to bring inside in the event of a storm. Having a list will help you remember things that may be broken or blown away in strong winds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_380">Keep trees and shrubbery trimmed. Make trees more wind resistant by removing diseased or damaged limbs, then strategically remove branches so that wind can blow through. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_381">Strong winds frequently break weak limbs and hurl them at great speed, causing damage or injury when they hit. Debris collection services may not be operating just before a storm, so it is best to do this well in advance of approaching storms..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_382">Remove any debris or loose items in your yard. Branches and firewood may become missiles in strong winds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_383">Consider installing permanent shutters to cover windows. Shutters can be closed quickly and provide the safest protection for windows..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_384">Strengthen garage doors. Garage doors are often damaged or destroyed by flying debris, allowing strong winds to enter. As winds apply pressure to the walls, the roof can be lifted off,and the rest of the house can easily follow..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_385">What to Do Before a Tornado.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_386">CORE ACTION MESSAGE.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_387">Watch for signs of a tornado..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_388">When the season, conditions, or forecast indicate the potential for tornadoes to form, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_389">If planning a trip or extended period of time outdoors, listen to the latest forecasts andtake necessary action if threatening weather is possible. Knowing what the weather couldbe helps you to be prepared..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_390">Have a raincoat, umbrella, and Disaster Supplies Kit handy so you can deal with severe weather if it occurs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_391">Watch for tornado danger signs. Tornadoes may strike so quickly that warnings cannot be issued long in advance. Pay attention to weather clues around you that warn of imminent danger:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_392">Dark, often greenish clouds. Sometimes one or more of the clouds turns greenish (aphenomenon caused by hail) indicating a tornado may develop..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_393">Wall cloud, an isolated lowering of the base of a thunderstorm. The wall cloud is particularly threatening if it is rotating..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_394">Large hail. Tornadoes are spawned from powerful thunderstorms, which are capable of producing large hail. Tornadoes frequently emerge from near the hail-producing portion ofthe storm..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_395">Cloud of debris. An approaching cloud of debris can mark the location of a tornado,even if a funnel is not visible.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_396">Funnel cloud. A visible rotating extension of the cloud base is a sign that a tornado may develop..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_397">Roaring noise. The high winds of a tornado can cause a roar that is often compared with the sound of a freight train..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_398">If a tornado watch is issued:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_399">CORE ACTION MESSAGES:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_400">Stay alert..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_401">Be alert to changing weather conditions. Tornadoes accompany severe thunderstorms,and weather conditions can change rapidly. Large hail, blowing debris, or the sound of anapproaching tornado may alert you. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_402">Many people say approaching tornadoes sound like a freight train..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_403">Bring your companion animals indoors and maintain direct control of them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_404">Be prepared to go to your tornado safe place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_405">If a tornado warning is issued:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_406">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_407">Go to your tornado safe room..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_408">If you are outside, go to the basement of a sturdy building if possible or lie flat in a low spot..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_409">If you are inside, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_410">Go to your safe place to protect yourself from glass and other flying objects. Take your pets with you, provided you can do so without endangering yourself. Tornadoes canchange direction, intensity, and speed very quickly. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_411">The tornado may be approaching your area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_412">Get under a sturdy piece of furniture, such as a workbench or heavy table, and hold on to it with one hand. Sturdy furniture will help protect you from falling debris..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_413">If tornado wind enters the room and the object moves, holding on with one hand will help you move with it, keeping you protected..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_414">Use your other arm and hand to protect your head and neck from falling or flying objects. Your head and neck are more easily injured than other parts of your body. Protect them as well as you can..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_415">Stay away from windows. Opening windows allows damaging winds to enter the structure. Leave the windows alone; instead, immediately go to your safe place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_416">It is a myth that tornadoes cause houses to explode due to changes in air pressure. Flying debris can shatter glass. Violent winds and debris slamming into buildings cause the most structural damage..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_417">If you are outside in a vehicle or mobile home, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_418">Go immediately to the basement of a nearby sturdy building. A sturdy building is the safest place to be. Tornado winds can blow large objects, including cars and mobilehomes, hundreds of feet away..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_419">Tornadoes can change direction quickly and can lift up a car or truck and toss it through the air; never try to out-drive a tornado. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_420">A mobile home can overturn very easily even if precautions have been taken to tie it down..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_421">If there is no building nearby, lie flat in a low spot and use your arms and hands to protect your head and neck. Tornadoes cause a lot of debris to be blown at very high speeds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_422">Dangerous flying debris can be blown under overpasses and bridges, and the structures themselves could be destroyed. You will be safer lying flat in a low-lying area where the wind and debris will blow above you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_423">Tornadoes come from severe thunderstorms, which can produce a lot of rain. If you see quickly rising water or floodwater coming toward you, move to another spot..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_424">Avoid places with wide-span roofs, such as auditoriums, cafeterias, large hallways,or shopping malls. Wide-span roofs are frequently damaged or destroyed in tornado winds; they provide less protection and more risk of injury than roofs over smaller rooms..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_425">What to Do After a Tornado.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_426">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_427">Help yourself, then others..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_428">Beware of dangers..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_429">You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_430">Continue listening to local radio or television stations or a NOAA Weather Radio for updated information and instructions. Access may be limited to some parts of the communityo r roads may be blocked..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_431">Check for injuries. Give first aid and get help for injured or trapped persons. Taking care of yourself first will allow you to help others safely until emergency responders arrive..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_432">Help people who require special assistance infants, elderly people, those without transportation, large families who may need additional help in an emergency situation, peoplewith disabilities, and the people who care for them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_433">Watch out for fallen power lines or broken gas lines and report them to the utility company immediately. Reporting potential hazards will get the utilities turned off as quicklyas possible, preventing further hazard and injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_434">Avoid damaged areas. Your presence might hamper rescue and other emergency operations and put you at further risk from the residual effects of tornadoes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_435">Stay out of damaged buildings..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_436">If you are away from home, return only when authorities say it is safe..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_437">Wear long pants, a long-sleeved shirt, and sturdy shoes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_438">Use battery-powered lanterns or flashlights when examining buildings. DO NOT USE CANDLES..; 4 50/51</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_439">Examine walls, floors, doors, staircases, and windows to make sure that the building is not in danger of collapsing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_440">Look for fire hazards. There may be broken or leaking gas lines, or damage to electrical systems. Clean up spilled medications, bleaches, gasoline, or other flammable liquids immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_441">Check for gas leaks. If you smell gas or hear a blowing or hissing noise, open a window andget everyone out quickly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_442">Turn off the gas using the outside main valve if you can, and call the gas company from a neighbor's home. If you turn off the gas for any reason, it must be turnedback on by a professional..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_443">Look for electrical system damage. If you see sparks or broken or frayed wires, or if you smell burning insulation, turn off the electricity at the main fuse box or circuit breaker..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_444">If you have to step in water to get to the fuse box or circuit breaker, call an electrician first for advice. Electrical equipment should be checked and dried before being returned to service..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_445">Watch for loose plaster, drywall, and ceilings that could fall..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_446">Take pictures of the damage, both of the building and its contents, for insurance claims..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_447">Use the telephone only for emergency calls. Telephone lines are frequently overwhelmed in disaster situations. They need to be clear for emergency calls to get through..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_448">Watch your animals closely. Keep all your animals under your direct control. Your pets maybe able to escape from your home or through a broken fence..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_449">Pets may become disoriented,particularly because tornadoes and the heavy rains that accompany them will usually affect scent markers that normally allow animals to find their homes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_450">The behavior of pets may change dramatically after any disruption, becoming aggressive or defensive, so be aware of their well-being and take measures to protect them from hazards, including displaced wild animals, and to ensure the safety of other people and animals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_451">Why talk about winter storms? Each year, exposure to cold, vehicle accidents caused by wintry roads, and fires caused by the improper use of heaters injure and kill hundreds of people in the United States. Add these to other winter weather hazards and you have a significant threat to human health and safety.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_452">A major winter storm can last for several days and can include high winds, freezing rain or sleet, heavy snowfall, and cold temperatures. People can become marooned at home without utilities or other services. Heavy snowfall and blizzards can trap motorists in their vehicles and make walking to find help a deadly effort. Storm effects, such as severely cold temperatures, heavy snow, and coastal flooding, can cause hazardous conditions and hidden problems. The aftermath of a winter storm can impact a community or region for days, weeks, or even months.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_453">What are winter storms? Winter storms can range from a moderate snow over a few hours to a blizzard with blinding, wind-driven snow that lasts for several days. Some winter storms are large enough to affect several states, while others affect only a single community. Many winter storms are accompanied by dangerously low temperatures and sometimes by strong winds, icing, sleet, and freezing rain.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_454">Winter storms are defined differently in various areas of the country, and each area is equipped differently to deal with the challenges and hazards of severe winter weather. A snowstorm that would be unremarkable in Buffalo, N.Y., could bring a city in the southern states to a standstill. Local emergency management offices, National Weather Service (NWS) offices, and American Red Cross chapters can provide definitions specific to each area.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_455">What damages can snow cause, and what are the different kinds of snow? Heavy snow can immobilize a region and paralyze a city, stranding commuters, closing airports, stopping the flow of supplies, and disrupting emergency and medical services. Accumulations of snow can cause roofs to collapse and knock down trees and power lines. Homes and farms may be isolated for days. In rural areas, unprotected livestock can be lost. In urban areas, the cost of snow removal, damage repair, and lost business can have severe economic impacts. In the mountains, heavy snow can lead to an avalanche—a mass of tumbling snow. More than 80 percent of midwinter avalanches are triggered by a rapid accumulation of snow, and 90 percent of those occur within 24 hours of snowfall. An avalanche can reach a mass of a million tons and travel at speeds up to 200 miles (322 kilometers) per hour.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_456">Various intensities of snow are defined differently:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_457">Blizzard describes winds of 35 miles (56 kilometers) per hour or more with snow and blowing snow that reduce visibility to less than one-quarter mile (0.4 kilometer) for at least three hours.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_458">Blowing snow describes wind-driven snow that reduces visibility. Blowing snow may be falling snow and/or snow on the ground that is picked up by the wind.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_459">Snow squall describes a brief, intense snow shower accompanied by strong, gusty winds. Accumulation from snow squalls can be significant.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_460">Snow shower describes snow that falls at varying intensities for short durations with little or no accumulation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_461">What damages can ice cause, and what are the different kinds of ice? Heavy accumulations of ice can bring down trees and topple utility poles and communication towers. Ice can disrupt communications and power for days while utility companies repair extensive damage. Even small accumulations of ice can be severely dangerous to motorists and pedestrians. Bridges and overpasses are particularly dangerous because they freeze before other surfaces.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_462">Ice forms in different ways:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_463">Sleet is rain that freezes into ice pellets before it reaches the ground. Sleet usually bounces when hitting a surface and does not stick to objects; however, it can accumulate like snow and cause roads and walkways to become hazardous.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_464">Freezing rain (also known as an ice storm) is rain that falls onto a surface that has a temperature below freezing. The cold surface causes the rain to freeze so the surfaces—trees, utility wires, vehicles, and roads—become glazed with ice. Even small accumulations of ice can cause significant hazards to people—especially pedestrians and motorists—and property.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_465">What damages can severe cold cause? What constitutes severe cold varies in different parts of the country. In some northern regions, cold temperatures are not considered severe until they are well below 0° F (−18° C). In most southern regions, near-freezing temperatures (around 32° F, or 0° C) are considered severe cold. Severe cold can cause much harm; for example, it can damage crops and other vegetation and freeze pipes causing them to burst. Unusually cold temperatures are especially dangerous in areas not accustomed to them because residents are generally unprepared and may not realize the dangers severe cold present.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_466">Exposure to cold can cause frostbite and life-threatening hypothermia. Frostbite is the freezing of body tissue, and it most frequently affects fingers, toes, earlobes, and the tip of the nose. Frostbite damage ranges from superficial and reversible to deep and permanent. Frostbite can result in tissue loss and even loss of digits and limbs.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_467">Hypothermia begins to occur when a person’s body temperature drops to 3° below its normal temperature. On average, a person would begin to suffer hypothermia if his or her temperature dropped to 96° F (35.6° C). Cold temperatures can cause hypothermia in anyone who is not adequately clothed or sheltered in a place with adequate heat. Hypothermia can kill people, and those who survive hypothermia are likely to suffer lasting ill effects. Infants and elderly people are the most susceptible. Elderly people account for the largest percentage of hypothermia victims, many of whom freeze to death in their own homes. Most of these victims are alone and their heating systems are working improperly or not at all. People who are taking certain medications, who have certain medical conditions, or who have been drinking alcohol also are at increased risk for hypothermia.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_468">What is winter flooding? Winter flooding can result from winter storms or long periods of cold temperatures, and it can cause significant damage and loss of life. The winds of intense winter storms can cause widespread tidal flooding and severe beach erosion along coastal areas. Long cold spells can cause rivers and lakes to freeze so that when a rise in the water level or a thaw breaks the ice into large chunks, the chunks become jammed at man-made and natural obstructions. These ice jams can act as dams, resulting in severe flooding. In addition, the sudden thawing of a heavy snow pack can often lead to flooding.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_469">How can I protect myself in winter storms? Winter storms are considered deceptive killers because most winter storm deaths are related only indirectly to the storms. Overall, most winter storm deaths result from vehicle or other transportation accidents caused by ice and snow. You should avoid driving when conditions include sleet, freezing rain or drizzle, snow, or dense fog. These are serious conditions that are often underestimated, and they make driving—and even walking outside—very hazardous.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_470">Exhaustion and heart attacks brought on by overexertion are two other common causes of deaths related to winter storms. Cold temperatures compound the strain of physical labor on a person’s body. Tasks such as shoveling snow, pushing a vehicle, or even walking in heavy snow can cause a heart attack, particularly in people who are older or not used to high levels of physical activity. Before tackling strenuous tasks in cold temperatures, you should carefully consider your physical condition, the weather factors, and the nature of the task. If you are not sure how much you can safely do, you should avoid all heavy work in cold temperatures.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_471">You should also dress to protect yourself from frostbite and hypothermia. When outside in cold temperatures, wear warm, loose-fitting, lightweight clothing in several layers. If you get too warm, you can remove one or more layers and if you get too cold you can add layers, so you can avoid the sweat-chills cycle. Your outer garments should be tightly woven, water repellent, and have a hood. Wear a hat. Half of your body heat can be lost from your head. Mittens, snug at the wrist, are better than gloves. Try to stay dry. If it is extremely cold, cover your mouth to protect your lungs.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_472">If, during severe cold, your home loses power or heat, go to a designated public shelter. For information on designated shelters, contact your local emergency management office or American Red Cross chapter.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_473">Home fires occur more frequently in the winter because people do not take the proper safety precautions when using alternative heating sources. Be sure all heating sources are installed according to local codes and permit requirements. To protect yourself, be sure that you never leave a fire unattended, that you dispose of ashes properly and only after they are completely cold, and that you operate and position space heaters only according to the manufacturer’s instructions. Use only space heaters approved by an independent testing laboratory. Fire during winter storms is exceptionally dangerous because conditions may make it difficult for firefighters to get to the fire, and the water needed to fight the fire may be frozen.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_474">In addition, every winter people are killed by carbon monoxide (CO) emitted by fuels they are using to heat their homes. Never operate unvented fuel-burning appliances in any closed room or where people are sleeping. CO poisoning from fuel-burning appliances kills people each year in the United States. Never use gas appliances such as ranges, ovens, or clothes dryers to heat your home. Do not use charcoal grills indoors or in attached garages.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_475">Never use a portable generator in an enclosed or partially enclosed space, including in your home, or in a garage, basement, crawl space, or other partially enclosed area, even with ventilation. Opening doors and windows or using fans will not prevent CO buildup. Locate a portable generator outdoors and away from doors, windows, and vents that could allow CO to come indoors. Portable generators can produce high levels of deadly CO very quickly. In addition to producing toxic engine exhaust, portable generators can cause electric shock or electrocution and fire. (See Appendix: Portable Generators.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_476">What is the best source of information about winter weather? Local radio or television stations or NOAA Weather Radio are the best sources of information about winter weather conditions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_477">NOAA Weather Radio is the prime alerting and critical information delivery system of the National Weather Service (NWS). NOAA Weather Radio broadcasts warnings, watches, forecasts, and other hazard information 24 hours a day over more than 650 stations in the 50 states, adjacent coastal waters, Puerto Rico, the U.S. Virgin Islands, and the U.S. Pacific territories.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_478">The NWS encourages people to buy a weather radio equipped with the Specific Area Message Encoder (SAME) feature. This feature automatically alerts you when important information about winter weather and other hazards is issued for your area. Information on NOAA Weather Radio is available from your local NWS office or at www.nws.noaa.gov/nwr.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_479">Wind Chill Temperature. The wind chill temperature is how cold people and animals feel when they are outside. Wind chill is based on the rate of heat loss from exposed skin caused by wind and cold. As wind increases, heat is carried away from the body at a faster rate. This drives down the body temperature. Therefore, the wind makes it feel much colder. The wind chill temperature is not the actual temperature but rather how wind and cold feel on exposed skin.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_480">Outlook, Watch, Warning, Advisory:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_481">A Winter Storm OUTLOOK means winter storm conditions are possible in the next two to five days. Stay tuned to local media for updates.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_482">A Winter Storm WATCH means winter storm conditions are possible within the next 36 to 48 hours. People in a watch area should review their winter storm plans (Family Disaster Plan, Disaster Supplies Kit) and keep informed about weather conditions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_483">A Winter Storm WARNING means life-threatening, severe winter conditions have begun or will begin within 24 hours. People in a warning area should take precautions immediately.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_484">A Blizzard WARNING means sustained winds or frequent gusts of 35 miles (56 kilometers) per hour or greater and considerable falling or blowing snow that reduces visibility to less than a quarter mile (0.4 kilometer) are expected to prevail for a period of three hours or longer. People in a warning area should take precautions immediately.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_485">A Winter Weather ADVISORY means winter weather conditions are expected to cause significant inconveniences and may be hazardous. If you are cautious, these situations should not be life threatening.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_486">Outlooks, watches, warnings, and advisories are issued by the National Weather Service (NWS) and broadcast on NOAA Weather Radio and on local radio and television stations.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_487">Is your community StormReady? To help people prepare for the ravages of hazardous weather, the National Weather Service has designed StormReady, a program aimed at arming America’s communities with the communication and safety skills necessary to save lives and property. More information is available at www.stormready.noaa.gov/.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_488">Carbon Monoxide Alarm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_489">Every home should have properly installed and maintained carbon monoxide (CO) alarms that meet current safety standards. (See Appendix: Carbon Monoxide Alarms.) CO alarms can help detect CO, a colorless, odorless gas produced by burning any fuel. Exposure to high levels of CO can cause death. The initial symptoms of CO poisoning are similar to the flu and include dizziness, fatigue, headache, nausea, and irregular breathing.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_490">Be Prepared for a Winter Storm. Protect Yourself. CORE ACTION MESSAGES:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_491">Install and maintain smoke and carbon monoxide alarms.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_492">Keep cold-weather clothing, supplies, and equipment ready.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_493">Inspect heating equipment and have it serviced as needed.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_494">For general preparedness, every household should create and practice a Family Disaster Plan and assemble and maintain a Disaster Supplies Kit. In addition, every household should take specific precautions and make specific plans for cold weather. If you live in an area where severe winter weather is possible, you should: Talk with members of your household about what to do if a winter storm watch or warning is issued. Discussing winter storms ahead of time helps reduce fear and helps everyone know how to respond during a winter storm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_495">Install smoke alarms. For new homes, interconnected smoke alarms are required on every level of the home, outside each sleeping area and inside each bedroom. Although this approach is ideal for all homes, as a minimum, existing homes should have smoke alarms on every level and outside each sleeping area. Test and maintain them according to the manufacturer’s instructions. (See Appendix: Smoke Alarms.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_496">Install carbon monoxide (CO) alarms following the manufacturer’s instructions. It is especially important to have one near sleeping areas. Test and maintain them according to the manufacturer’s instructions. (See Appendix: Carbon Monoxide Alarms.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_497">Get training. Take an American Red Cross first aid course to learn how to treat exposure to the cold, frostbite, and hypothermia.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_498">Service snow removal equipment before the winter storm season and maintain it in good working order.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_499">Keep your vehicle’s gas tank full so you can leave right away in an emergency and to keep the fuel line from freezing.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_500">Keep a supply of non-clumping kitty litter to make walkways and steps less slippery. Kitty litter temporarily improves traction on an icy surface. Rock salt melts ice on walkways, but it can damage vegetation and concrete. You may find other, less damaging, ice-melting products at building supplies stores.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_501">Keep handy a warm coat, gloves or mittens, hat, water-resistant boots, and extra blankets and warm clothing for each member of the household.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_502">Make sure your home heating sources are installed according to local codes and permit requirements and are clean and in working order. Many home fires are started by poorly maintained furnaces or stoves, cracked or rusted furnace parts, or chimneys with creosote buildup.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_503">Be sure all portable and fixed electric space heaters have been certified by an independent testing laboratory. Keep blankets, clothing, curtains, furniture, and anything that could get hot and catch fire at least three feet away from all heat sources. Plug heaters directly into the wall socket rather than using an extension cord and unplug them when they are not in use</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_504">Use kerosene heaters only if permitted by law in your area. Refuel kerosene heaters outdoors only after they have cooled. Kerosene has a low flash point. If mistakenly dripped on hot surfaces, it can cause fires. Do not substitute gasoline for kerosene in the heater. Make sure the area is ventilated properly. Follow all of the manufacturer’s instructions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_505">Have chimneys and wood stoves inspected annually and cleaned if necessary. Chimneys and wood stoves build up creosote, which is the residue left behind by burning wood. Creosote is flammable and needs to be professionally removed periodically. Store ashes in a metal container with a tight-fitting lid.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_506">Bring your companion animals inside during winter weather.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_507">Protect Your Property. CORE ACTION MESSAGES:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_508">Guard against fire and CO poisoning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_509">Insulate your home and protect the pipes.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_510">If you live in an area where severe winter weather is possible, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_511">Make sure your home is properly insulated. If necessary, insulate the walls and attic to reduce your home's power demands for heat. Caulk and weather-strip doors and windowsills to keep cold air out.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_512">Install storm windows or cover windows with plastic from the inside to provide an extra layer of insulation to keep cold air out.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_513">Protect pipes from freezing by:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_514">Wrapping pipes in insulation or layers of newspaper and then covering them with plastic to keep out moisture.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_515">Letting faucets drip a little.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_516">Know how to shut off the main water valve and how to shut off and drain outside faucets. Outside faucets are often controlled by a valve inside the home. Keep a wrench near the valves.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_517">Install heat tape on water pipes. Put the tape on all exterior water pipes and interior pipes located on outside walls or anywhere else that temperatures could go below freezing. Follow carefully the manufacturer’s instructions for installation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_518">If the pipes freeze, remove any insulation or newspaper and wrap the pipes in rags. Completely open all faucets and pour hot water over the pipes, starting where they were most exposed to the cold or where the cold most likely penetrated. A hand-held hair dryer, used with caution to prevent overheating, also works well.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_519">Consider buying emergency heating equipment, such as a wood- or coal-burning stove or an electric or kerosene heater. If you have a stove, be sure it is properly vented and in good working order and that you dispose of ashes safely. Keep a supply of wood or coal on hand. If you have an electric space heater, either portable or fixed, be sure it is certified by an independent testing laboratory. Plug a heater directly into the wall socket rather than using an extension cord and unplug it when it is not in use. Use a kerosene heater only if permitted by law in your area; check with your local fire department. If you have a kerosene heater, use only the correct fuel for your unit. Properly ventilate the area of use. Refuel the unit outdoors only, and only when the unit is cool. Follow all of the manufacturer's instructions. Keep all heaters at least three feet away from furniture and other flammable objects.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_520">When using fireplaces, stoves, and space heaters, ventilate properly and guard against fire. Using alternative sources of heat such as these greatly increases your risk for fire and carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_521">Consider storing sufficient heating fuel. Regular fuel sources may be cut off. Be cautious of fire hazards when storing any type of fuel.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_522">If you have a fireplace, consider keeping a supply of firewood or coal. Be sure the fireplace is properly vented and in good working order and that you dispose of ashes safely.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_523">Install snow fences in rural areas to reduce drifting snow on roads and paths, which could block access to homes, barns, and animals' feed and water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_524">Create a place where your animals can be comfortable in severe winter weather. Bring your companion animals indoors. Horses and livestock should have a shelter where they can be protected from wind, snow, ice, and rain. Grazing animals should have access to a protected supply of food and non-frozen water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_525">Be aware of the potential for flooding when snow and ice melt and be sure that your animals have access to high ground that is not impeded by fencing or other barriers. You may not be able to get to them in time to relocate them in the event of flooding.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_526">Ensure that any outbuildings that house or shelter animals can withstand wind and heavy snow and ice.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_527">Consider purchasing flood insurance, if you live in a flood-prone area, to cover possible flood damage that may occur during the spring thaw. Homeowners' policies do not cover damage from floods. Ask your insurance agent about the National Flood Insurance Program (NFIP) if you are at risk. More information on NFIP is available at www.fema.gov/nfip.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_528">What to Do Before a Winter Storm. CORE ACTION MESSAGES:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_529">Stay informed.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_530">Know the location of public shelters.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_531">You should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_532">Keep handy a battery-powered radio or television or NOAA Weather Radio with the Specific Area Message Encoder (SAME) feature.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_533">Contact your local emergency management office or American Red Cross chapter for information on designated public shelters in case you lose power or heat.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_534">Check your Disaster Supplies Kit, and keep it handy.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_535">Be sure you have ample heating fuel.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_536">If you have alternative heating sources, such as fireplaces, wood- or coal-burning stoves, or space heaters, be sure they are installed according to local codes and permit requirements and are clean and in working order.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_537">Check that your fire extinguisher(s) is in good working order, and replace it if necessary. (See Appendix: Fire Extinguishers.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_538">Bring your companion animals inside and ensure that your horses and livestock have blankets if appropriate and unimpeded access to shelter, food, and non-frozen water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_539">What to Do During a Winter Storm Watch. CORE ACTION MESSAGES:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_540">Stay informed.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_541">Shelter animals.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_542">Stay inside if possible.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_543">Stay indoors and wear warm clothes. Layers of loose-fitting, lightweight, warm clothing will keep you warmer than a bulky sweater. If you feel too warm, remove layers to avoid sweating; if you feel chilled, add layers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_544">Listen to a local station on battery-powered radio or television or to NOAA Weather Radio for updated emergency information.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_545">Bring your companion animals inside before the storm begins.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_546">Eat regularly. Food provides the body with energy for producing its own heat.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_547">Keep the body replenished with fluids to prevent dehydration. Drink liquids such as warm broth or juice. Avoid caffeine and alcohol. Caffeine, a stimulant, accelerates the symptoms of hypothermia. Alcohol, such as brandy, is a depressant and hastens the effects of cold on the body. Alcohol also slows circulation and can make you less aware of the effects of cold. Both caffeine and alcohol can cause dehydration.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_548">Conserve fuel. Winter storms can last for several days. Great demand may be placed on electric, gas, and other fuel distribution systems (fuel oil, propane, etc.). Suppliers of propane and fuel oil may not be able to replenish depleted supplies during severe weather. Electric and gas services may be temporarily disrupted when many people demand large amounts at the same time. Lower the thermostat to 65° F (18° C) during the day and to 55° F (13° C) at night. Close off unused rooms, and stuff towels or rags in cracks under the doors. Cover the windows at night.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_549">If you must go outside, protect yourself from winter storm hazards:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_550">Wear layered clothing, mittens or gloves, and a hat. Layered clothing will keep you warmer than a single, heavy coat. Outer garments should be tightly woven and water repellent. Mittens or gloves and a hat will prevent the loss of body heat. Mittens are warmer than gloves because your fingers maintain more warmth when they touch each other. Half of your body-heat loss is from your head.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_551">Cover your mouth to protect your lungs from severely cold air. Avoid taking deep breaths; minimize talking.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_552">Watch for signs of hypothermia and frostbite. (See Appendix: Frostbite and Hypothermia.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_553">Keep dry. Change wet clothing frequently to prevent a loss of body heat. Wet clothing loses much of its insulating value and transmits heat rapidly away from the body.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_554">Stretch before you go out. If you go out to shovel snow, do a few stretching exercises to warm up your body. This will reduce your chances of muscle injury.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_555">Avoid overexertion, such as shoveling heavy snow, pushing a vehicle, or walking in deep snow. The strain from the cold and the hard labor may cause a heart attack.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_556">Sweating could lead to a chill and hypothermia.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_557">Walk carefully on snowy, icy sidewalks. Slips and falls occur frequently in winter weather, resulting in painful and sometimes disabling injuries.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_558">If you must go out during a winter storm, use public transportation if possible. About 70 percent of winter deaths related to ice and snow occur in automobiles.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_559">Check on relatives, neighbors, and friends, particularly if they are elderly or if they live alone.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_560">Driving in Winter Conditions. CORE ACTION MESSAGES:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_561">Winterize your vehicle and stock it with emergency supplies.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_562">Avoid driving in a winter storm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_563">If stranded, stay with the vehicle and keep warm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_564">You should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_565">Have your vehicle winterized before the winter storm season. Keeping your vehicle in good condition will decrease your chance of being stranded in cold weather. Have a mechanic check your battery, antifreeze, wipers and windshield washer fluid, ignition system, thermostat, lights, flashing hazard lights, exhaust system, heater, brakes, defroster, and oil level. If necessary, replace existing oil with winter-grade oil. Install good winter tires. Make sure the tires have adequate tread. All-weather radials are usually adequate for most winter conditions. However, some jurisdictions require that vehicles on their roads be equipped with chains or snow tires with studs.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_566">Check your vehicle emergency supplies kit and replenish it if necessary. (See Appendix: Emergency Supplies for Your Vehicle.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_567">If you will be driving in wintry conditions, in addition to the usual emergency supplies you keep in your vehicle, be sure to keep enough of the following for each person:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_568">Blankets or sleeping bags.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_569">Rain gear, extra sets of dry clothing, mittens, socks, and wool hats.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_570">Newspapers for insulation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_571">Plastic bags for sanitation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_572">Canned fruit, nuts, and high energy "munchies." (Include a non-electric can opener if necessary.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_573">Keep in your vehicle:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_574">A windshield scraper and small broom for ice and snow removal.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_575">A small sack of sand for generating traction under wheels and a set of tire chains or traction mats.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_576">Matches in a waterproof container.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_577">Cards, games, and puzzles.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_578">A brightly colored (preferably red) cloth to tie to the antenna.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_579">Keep a cell phone or two-way radio with you when traveling in winter. Make sure the battery is charged.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_580">If you must be on the road during a winter storm, bring warm broth in a thermos and several bottles of water for each person.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_581">Keep your vehicle’s gas tank full so you will be ready in case of emergency and to prevent the fuel line from freezing.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_582">Plan to travel during daylight and, if possible, take at least one other person with you.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_583">Let someone know your destination, your route, and when you expect to arrive. Ifyour vehicle gets stuck along the way, help can be sent along your predetermined route.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_584">Before leaving, listen to weather reports for your area and the areas you will be passing through, or call the state highway patrol for the latest road conditions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_585">Be on the lookout for sleet, freezing rain, freezing drizzle, and dense fog, which can make driving very hazardous.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_586">Avoid traveling during a winter storm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_587">If you must travel and do become stranded, it is better to stay in the vehicle and wait for help. Do not leave the vehicle to search for assistance unless help is visible within 100 yards (91 meters). You can quickly become disoriented and confused in blowing snow.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_588">If you are stuck in a vehicle:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_589">Display a trouble sign to indicate you need help. Hang a brightly colored cloth (preferably red) on the radio antenna and raise the hood after snow stops falling.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_590">Run the engine occasionally to keep warm. Carbon monoxide can build up inside a standing vehicle while the engine is running, even if the exhaust pipe is clear. Running the heater for 10 minutes every hour generally is enough to keep the occupants warm. Running the engine for only short periods reduces the risk of carbon monoxide poisoning and conserves fuel. Turn on the engine for about 10 minutes each hour (or five minutes every half hour). Use the heater while the engine is running. Keep the exhaust pipe clear of snow, and slightly open a downwind window for ventilation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_591">Leave the overhead light on when the engine is running so that you can be seen.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_592">Do light exercises to keep up circulation. Clap your hands and move your arms and legs occasionally. Try not to stay in one position for too long.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_593">If more than one person is in the vehicle, take turns sleeping. One of the first signs of hypothermia is sleepiness. If you are not awakened periodically to increase body temperature and circulation, you can freeze to death.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_594">Huddle together for warmth. Use newspapers, maps, and even the removable floor mats for added insulation. Layering items will help trap more body heat.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_595">Watch for signs of frostbite and hypothermia. Severe cold can cause numbness, making you unaware of possible danger. Keep fingers and toes moving for circulation, and drink warm broth to reduce the risk of further injury.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_596">Drink fluids to avoid dehydration. Bulky winter clothing can cause you to sweat, but cold dry air will help the sweat evaporate, making you unaware of possible dehydration. When people are dehydrated, they are more susceptible to the ill effects of cold and to heart attacks.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_597">Avoid overexertion. Cold weather puts an added strain on the heart. Unaccustomed exercise, such as shoveling snow or pushing a vehicle, can bring on a heart attack or make other medical conditions worse.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_598">What to Do After a Winter Storm. CORE ACTION MESSAGES:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_599">Stay informed.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_600">Avoid travel.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_601">Avoid overexertion.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_602">You should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_603">Keep listening to a local radio or television station or NOAA Weather Radio for updated information and instructions. Access to some parts of the community may be limited or roads may be blocked.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_604">Help people who require special assistance—infants, elderly people, those without transportation, large families who may need additional help in an emergency situation, people with disabilities, and the people who care for them.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_605">Avoid driving and other travel until conditions have improved. Roads may be blocked by snow or emergency vehicles.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_606">Avoid overexertion. Heart attacks from shoveling heavy snow are a leading cause of death during the winter.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_607">Keep up with local weather forecasts and be prepared when you go outside. Major winter storms are often followed by even colder conditions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_608">Check on your animals and ensure that their access to food and water is unimpeded by drifted snow, ice, or other obstacles.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_609">For information on portable-generator safety and carbon monoxide poisoning, see Appendix: Portable Generators.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_610">Media and Community Education Ideas:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_611">Sponsor a "Winter Weather Awareness Day" a week or so before winter storm season begins. This is a good way to get emergency management officials and local Red Cross</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_612">representatives involved.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_613">Ask your local newspaper or radio or television station to:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_614">Do a series on the dangers of winter storms and severe cold, with special emphasis on what people should do if they are caught out in the open or in a vehicle.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_615">Highlight the importance of staying informed about local weather conditions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_616">Run public service ads about how to protect lives in winter storms and extreme cold. Help the reporters to localize the information by providing them with the local emergency telephone number for the fire, police, and emergency medical services departments (usually 9-1-1) and emergency numbers for the local utilities and hospitals. Also provide business telephone numbers for the local emergency management office and American Red Cross chapter.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_617">Inform your community about the different National Weather Service announcements— winter storm outlook, winter storm watch, winter storm warning, blizzard warning, winter weather advisory.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_618">In the fall, present information sessions about safe practices for the coming season of cold weather and winter storms. Include information on alternative heat sources and home insulation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_619">Interview local physicians about the dangers of hypothermia and other winter health conditions. Include discussions of exhaustion and heart attacks caused by overexertion.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_620">Advise people of the dangers of winter driving, and warn them that driving in winter storms can be a risk to their lives. Produce a series of announcements on what people should do if they are stuck in a vehicle during a blizzard.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_621">Facts and Fiction:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_622">Fiction: If you are stuck in a car in a snowstorm, the best thing to do is to get out and look for help.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_623">Facts: You should stay in your vehicle and wait for rescuers. If you leave your vehicle in wind-driven snow, you could quickly become disoriented. Make the vehicle visible to rescuers (tie a colored cloth to the antenna or door, turn on the dome light when running the engine for heat, raise the hood when the snow stops falling). If you have a cell phone, call a towing company or 9-1-1 or the local emergency number.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_624">Fiction: In severe cold, it is best to stay warm by wearing a very heavy coat.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_625">Facts: You should wear loose, lightweight, warm clothes in layers. Trapped air insulates. Remove layers to avoid perspiration and subsequent chill. Outer garments should be tightly woven, water repellent, and hooded. Wear a hat. Half your body-heat loss can be from the head. Cover your mouth to protect your lungs from extreme cold. Mittens, snug at the wrist, are better than gloves. Try to stay dry.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_626">Why talk about winter storms?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_627">What are winter storms?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_628">What damages can snow cause, and what are the different kinds of snow?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_629">What damages can ice cause, and what are the different kinds of ice?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_630">What damages can severe cold cause?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_631">What is winter flooding?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_632">How can I protect myself in winter storms?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_633">Be Prepared for a Winter Storm/Protect Yourself; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_634">What to Do Before a Winter Storm; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_635">What to Do During a Winter Storm Watch; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_636">What to Do During a Winter Storm Warning or a Blizzard Warning; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_637">What to Do After a Winter Storm; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_638">Driving in Winter Conditions; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_639">Protect Your Property; CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_640">If you live in an area where severe winter weather is possible, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_641">Various intensities of snow are defined differently:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_642">Ice forms in different ways (def.):</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_643">Wind Chill Temperature (def.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_644">Is your community StormReady?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_645">What is the best source of information about winter weather?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_646">Media and Community Education Ideas.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_647">Local emergency management office, American Red Cross chapter, Local radio or television stations, NOAA Weather Radio/NWS/SAME.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_648">ACFAS is the American National Red Cross Advisory Council on First Aid and Safety.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_649">Outlook, Watch, Warning, Advisory: Winter Storm OUTLOOK , Winter Storm WATCH, Winter Storm WARNING, Blizzard WARNING, Winter Weather ADVISORY (def.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_650">Sheltering, Evacuation, Post-disaster Safety.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_651">Frostbite ,Hypothermia, Dihydration, Exhaustion, Heart attacks.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_652">CO poisoning, Burns.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_653">Protective dress.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_654">Portable Generators, Snow shovell, window shutters.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_655">Smoke/Carbon Monoxide Alarm, Fire extinguisher.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_656">Residential fire.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_657">Emergency flashers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_658">National Fire Protection Association, U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_659">Checklist, Family Disaster Plan, Disaster Supplies Kit, MedKit, pet disaster kit.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_660">Special Flood Hazard Area, National Flood Insurance Program (NFIP), StormReady.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_661">www.nws.noaa.gov/nwr, www.stormready.noaa.gov/, www.fema.gov/nfip.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_662">Business and Home Safety at www.ibhs.org.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_663">Rural, Urban.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_664">Facts and Fiction.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_665">Sightseers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_666">snowdrifts, precipitation, with heavy precipitation and hurricane force winds, it caused a blizzard over much of the area it affected, including thundersnow , Ice pellets, public works facilities, tempest, state of emergency, plowed snow , visibility, nor'easter, polar jet stream, Highway travel was closed or restricted, cabins and lodges, rapid pressure drop, blowing snow, wind gusts, extra-tropical cyclone,</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_667">squall line, cold front, storm surge, stationary front, arctic high pressure system, extratropical area of low pressure, Barometric pressures, Saffir-Simpson hurricane scale, whiteout, NCDC, supercells, low pressure system,</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_668">No Name Storm, Storm of the Century, Derecho,</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_669">snowmobiles,</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_670">Meteorological Operations Division (MOD), National Meteorological Center (NMC), National Weather Service (NWS), medium-term (i.e., 3 to 5 days) and short-term (i.e., 12 hours to 2 days) forecasts, Property Claim Services (PCS) unit of the Insurance Services Office (ISO), National Flood Insurance Program (NFIP), RMS ® U.S. Winterstorm Model, RMS ® U.S. Severe Convective Storm Model, numerical weather prediction (NWP), modes of damage (snow, wind, ice, and freezing temperatures),</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_671">Floods and Flash Floods.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_672">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_673">Determine your risk..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_674">Prepare members of your household..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_675">Find out the elevation above flood stage of your home, out buildings, and pastures or corrals. Knowing the elevation of your property in relation to nearby streams and dams will let you know if forecasted flood levels will affect your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_676">Find out if local streams or rivers flood easily..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_677">Talk with members of your household about the possibility of floods and flash floods and what to do to stay safe if one occurs. Knowing how to respond will reduce fear and save precious time in an emergency..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_678">Find out about the flood evacuation routes in your area and develop a flood evacuation plan for your household. (See chapter on Evacuation and Sheltering, and Post-disaster Safety.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_679">All members of the household should know where to meet each other, where to evacuate to, and what route(s) to take if they have to leave. Making plans well in advance will help you avoid last-minute confusion..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_680">Find out if you are located in a floodplain, which is considered a Special Flood Hazard Area. If you are, you are still eligible for flood insurance..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_681">Check with your city or county government (start with the Building or Planning Department) to review the Flood Insurance Rate Maps, published by the Federal Emergency Management Agency(FEMA). If your home is especially vulnerable, consider relocation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_682">Use a NOAA Weather Radio or listen to local stations on a portable, battery powered radio or television for updated emergency information..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_683">If you live in a frequently flooded area, stockpile emergency building materials.These include plywood, plastic sheeting, lumber, nails, hammer and saw, pry bar, sand,shovels, and sandbags..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_684">Protect Your Property.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_685">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_686">Protect important papers and equipment..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_687">If you are at risk from floods, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_688">Keep insurance policies, documents, and other valuables in a safe-deposit box.You may need quick, easy access to these documents. Keep them in a safe place less likely to be damaged during a flood..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_689">Raise your furnace, water heater, and electric panel to higher floors or the attic if they are in areas of your home that may be flooded. Raising this equipment will prevent damage..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_690">An undamaged water heater may be your best source of fresh water after a flood..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_691">Install check valves in plumbing to prevent floodwater from backing up into the drains of your home. As a last resort, when floods threaten, use large corks or stoppers to plug showers, tubs, or basins..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_692">Construct barriers such as levees, berms, and flood walls to stop floodwater from entering the building. Permission to construct such barriers may be required by local building codes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_693">Check local building codes and ordinances for safety requirements..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_694">Seal walls in basements with waterproofing compounds to avoid see page through cracks..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_695">Ensure that any out buildings, pastures, or corrals are protected in the same way as your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_696">When installing or changing fence lines, consider placing them in such away that your animals are able to move to higher ground in the event of flooding..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_697">Sand Bags.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_698">If flooding is expected, consider using sand bags to keep water away from your home. It takes two people about one hour to fill and place 100 sand bags, giving you a wall one foot (0.3 meter) high and 20 feet (6meters) long..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_699">Make sure you have enough sand, burlap or plastic bags, shovels, strong helpers, and time to place them properly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_700">Avert the Dangers of Flood and Flash Flood.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_701">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_702">Listen for and respond to watches and warnings..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_703">If advised to evacuate or if you think you are in danger, leave immediately.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_704">Prepare your home if you have time..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_705">Even when there are no signs of a flood, be alert to conditions that can cause floods:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_706">Heavy rain for several hours, or steady rain for several days, can saturate the groundand cause a flood..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_707">Distant thunder indicates a distant thunderstorm that could send runoff your way. Run off can produce a deadly flash flood that appears with no warning, particularly in certain types of terrain, for example, in an arroyo or streambed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_708">Other distant events, such as a dam break or the sudden unclogging of an ice jam, can cause flash floods..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_709">Park a vehicle or set up camp away from streams and washes, particularly during threatening conditions. Floodwater can rise quickly and carry you, your vehicle, or your belongings away..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_710">Watch, Warning.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_711">A Flood WATCH means a flood is possible in your area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_712">A Flood WARNING means flooding is already occurring or will occur soon in your area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_713">A Flash Flood WATCH means flash flooding is possible in your area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_714">A Flash Flood WARNING means a flash flood is occurring or will occur very soon..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_715">A watch is the first official alert that a flash flood or flood may occur in a specific area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_716">People in a watch area should review their flood plans (Family Disaster Plan, Disaster Supplies Kit, evacuation routes), keep informed, and be ready to act if a warning is issued or if flooding occurs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_717">What to Do Before a Flood.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_718">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_719">Use NOAA Weather Radio or listen continuously to a local radio or television station..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_720">Be ready to evacuate immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_721">Follow authorities instructions..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_722">Save lives, not belongings..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_723">If a flood or flash flood watch is issued for your area, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_724">Use a NOAA Weather Radio or listen continuously to a local station on a portable,battery-powered radio or television..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_725">Be ready to act quickly. Floods and flash floods can happen quickly and without warning. Be ready to act immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_726">Be alert to signs of flooding, and, if you live in a flood-prone area, be ready to evacuate at a moment's notice. Floods can happen quickly and you may need to leave with little or no notice..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_727">Follow the instructions and advice of local authorities. Local authorities are the most informed about affected areas and the most knowledgeable about areas you should avoid..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_728">If your home is in a flood-prone area:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_729">Fill plastic bottles with clean water for drinking. (See Appendix: Storing Water.) Water may become contaminated or water service may be interrupted..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_730">Fill bathtubs and sinks with water for flushing the toilet or washing the floor or clothing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_731">Adults can use this water for bathing, but young children should not bathe in water that has been stored in glazed tubs and sinks because over time lead can leach into the water from the glaze..;12 50/51 57</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_732">Bring outdoor belongings, such as patio furniture, indoors. Unsecured items may be swept away and damaged by floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_733">Move your furniture and valuables to higher floors of your home. If floodwater affects your home, higher floors are less likely to be damaged..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_734">Turn off utilities if told to do so by authorities. Authorities may ask you to turn off water or electric utilities to prevent damage to your home or within the community..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_735">Most of the time they will tell you to leave the gas on because, if you shut it off, a professional is required to turn your gas back on, and it may be several weeks before you receive service..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_736">Turn off propane tanks. Propane tanks may be damaged or dislodged by strong winds or water. Turning them off reduces the fire potential..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_737">Unplug small appliances. Small appliances may be affected by electrical power surges that may occur. Unplugging them reduces potential damage.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_738">Keep your previously assembled Disaster Supplies Kit near. You may need to act quickly. Having your supplies ready will save time..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_739">Fill your car's gas tank, in case an evacuation notice is issued. If electric power is cut off, gas stations may not be able to operate pumps for several days..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_740">Be prepared to evacuate. Local officials may ask you to leave if they conclude that your home is at risk from floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_741">Consider a precautionary evacuation of your animals, especially any large or numerous animals. Waiting until the last minute could be fatal for them and dangerous for you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_742">Where possible, move livestock to higher ground. If you are using a horse or other trailer to evacuate your animals, move early rather than wait until it may be too late to maneuver a trailer through slow traffic..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_743">If a flood or flash flood warning is issued for your area, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_744">Use a NOAA Weather Radio or listen continuously to a local station on a portable,battery-powered radio or television..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_745">Be alert to signs of flooding. A warning means a flood is imminent or is happening in the area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_746">Bring your companion animals indoors and maintain direct control of them. Be sure that your pet disaster kit and your family Disaster Supplies Kit are ready to go incase you need to evacuate..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_747">If you live in a flood-prone area or think you are at risk, evacuate immediately. Move quickly to higher ground. Save yourself, not your belongings. The most important thing is your safety..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_748">If advised by authorities to evacuate, do so immediately. Move to a safe area before access is cut off by floodwater. Evacuation is much simpler and safer before flood water becomes too deep for vehicles to drive through..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_749">Follow the instructions and advice of local authorities. Local authorities are the most informed about affected areas and the most knowledgeable about areas you should avoid..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_750">Follow recommended evacuation routes. Shortcuts or alternative, non-recommended routes may be blocked or damaged by floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_751">Leave early enough to avoid being marooned by flooded roads. Delaying too long may allow all escape routes to become blocked..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_752">If you evacuate, take your animals with you. If it is not safe for you, it is not safe for your animals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_753">What to Do During a Flood or Flash Flood.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_754">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_755">Climb to high ground..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_756">Get away from standing, flowing, or rising water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_757">If you are outdoors, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_758">Stay out of areas subject to flooding. Dips, low spots, canyons, washes, etc. canbecome filled with water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_759">Climb to high ground and stay there. Move away from dangerous floodwater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_760">If you come upon a flowing stream where water is above your ankles, stop, turnaround, and go another way..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_761">Never try to walk, swim, or drive through swift water.Many flood fatalities are caused by people attempting to drive through water, or people playing in high water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_762">If it is moving swiftly, even water six inches (15 centimeters) deep can sweep you off your feet...</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_763">If you are driving, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_764">Avoid already flooded areas, and areas subject to sudden flooding. Do not attempt to cross flowing streams or water covered roads. As little as six inches of water may cause you to lose control of your vehicle..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_765">The National Weather Service reports that nearly half of all flood fatalities are vehicle related. The depth of water is not always obvious. The roadbed may be washed out under the water, and you could be stranded or trapped..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_766">Also, standing water may be electrically charged from underground or downed power lines. Rapidly rising water may stall the engine, engulf the vehicle and its occupants, and sweep them away..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_767">Look out for flooding at highway dips, bridges, and low areas. Two feet (0.6 meters) of water will carry away most vehicles, including SUVs and pickup trucks..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_768">Stay away from underpasses. Underpasses can fill rapidly with water, while the adjacent roadway remains clear. Driving into an underpass can quickly put you in five to six feet (1.5 to 1.8 meters) of water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_769">Turn around and find another route if you come upon rapidly rising water. Move to higher ground away from rivers, streams, creeks, and storm drains..;12 50/51</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_770">If your route is blocked by floodwater or barricades, find another route. Barricades are put up by local officials to protect people from unsafe roads. Driving around them can be a serious risk..;12 50/51</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_771">What to Do After a Flood or Flash Flood.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_772">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_773">Help yourself, then help others..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_774">Stay away from damaged areas..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_775">Get medical care at the nearest hospital or clinic, if necessary. Contaminated floodwater can cause infection. Severe injuries will require medical attention..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_776">Help people who require special assistanceinfants, elderly people, those without transportation, large families who may need additional help in an emergency situation,people with disabilities, and the people who care for them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_777">Stay away from damaged areas. Your presence might hamper rescue and other emergency operations, and put you at further risk from the residual effects of floods,such as contaminated water, crumbled roads, landslides, mud flows, and other hazards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_778">Continue to listen to NOAA Weather Radio or a local radio or television station and return home only when authorities indicate it is safe to do so..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_779">Flood dangers do not end when the water begins to recede; there may be flood-related hazards within your community, which you could hear about from local broadcasts..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_780">Stay out of any building if floodwater remains around the building. Floodwater often undermines foundations, causing sinking. Floors can crack or break and buildingscan collapse..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_781">Avoid entering any building (home, business, or other) before local officials have said it is safe to do so. Buildings may have hidden damage that makes them unsafe.Gas leaks or damage to electric lines or water lines can create additional problems..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_782">Report broken utility lines to the appropriate authorities. Reporting potential hazards will get the utilities turned off as quickly as possible, preventing further hazardand injury..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_783">Avoid smoking inside buildings. Smoking in confined areas can cause fires.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_784">When entering buildings, use extreme caution. Building damage may have occurredwhere you least expect it. Watch carefully every step you take..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_785">Wear long pants, a long-sleeved shirt, and sturdy shoes. The most common injury following a disaster is cut feet..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_786">Use battery-powered lanterns or flashlights when examining buildings. DO NOT USE CANDLES..;12 50/51 68</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_787">Examine walls, floors, doors, staircases, and windows to make sure that the building is not in danger of collapsing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_788">Inspect foundations for cracks or other damage. Cracks and damage to a foundation can render a building uninhabitable..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_789">Look for fire hazards. There may be broken or leaking gas lines, flooded electrical circuits, or submerged furnaces or electrical appliances..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_790">Flammable or explosive materials may have traveled from upstream. Fire is the most frequent hazard following floods..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_791">Check for gas leaks. If you smell gas or hear a blowing or hissing noise, open a window and get everyone outside quickly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_792">Turn off the gas at the outside main valve if you can and call the gas company from a neighbor's home. If you turn off the gas for any reason, it must be turned back on by a professional..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_793">Look for electrical system damage. If you see sparks or broken or frayed wires, or if you smell burning insulation, turn off the electricity at the main fuse box or circuit breaker..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_794">If you have to step in water to get to the fuse box or circuit breaker, call an electrician first for advice. Electrical equipment should be checked and dried before being returned to service..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_795">Check for damage to sewage and water lines. If you suspect sewage lines are damaged, avoid using the toilets and call a plumber. If water pipes are damaged, contact the water company and avoid using water from the tap..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_796">You can obtain safe water from undamaged water heaters or by melting ice cubes that were made before the pipes weredamaged. Turn off the main water valve before draining water from these sources..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_797">Watch out for wild animals, especially poisonous snakes, that may have come into buildings with the floodwater. Use a stick to poke through debris. Floodwater flushessnakes and many animals out of their homes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_798">Watch for loose plaster, drywall, and ceilings that could fall..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_799">Take pictures of the damage, both of the building and its contents, for insurance claims..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_800">Watch your animals closely. Keep all your animals under your direct control. Hazardous materials abound in flooded areas. Your pets may be able to escape fromyour home or through a broken fence..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_801">Pets may become disoriented, particularly because flooding usually affects scent markers that normally allow them to find theirhomes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_802">The behavior of pets may change dramatically after any disruption, becoming aggressive or defensive, so be aware of their well-being and take measures to protect them from hazards, including displaced wild animals, and to ensure the safety of other ....</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_803">After returning home, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_804">Throw away food and drinking water that has come in contact with floodwater,including canned goods..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_805">It is impossible to know if containers were damaged and the seals compromised. Food contaminated by floodwater can cause severe infections..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_806">Discard wooden spoons, plastic utensils, and baby bottle nipples and pacifiers if they have been covered by floodwater. There is no way to safely clean them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_807">Disinfect metal pans and utensils by boiling them in clean or properly treated water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_808">If water is of questionable purity, boil the water or add bleach to it, and then distill the water if you will be drinking it. (See Appendix: Drinking Water Safety.) .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_809">Wells inundated by floodwater should be pumped out and the water tested for purity before drinking. If in doubt, call your local public health authority. Ill health effects often occur when people drink water contaminated with bacteria and germs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_810">Avoid drinking or preparing food with tap water until you are certain it is notcontaminated. Floodwater may have contaminated public water supplies or wells. Local officials should advise you on the safety of the drinking water..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_811">Pump out flooded basements gradually (about one-third of the water per day) to avoid structural damage..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_812">If the water is pumped out completely in a short period of time, pressure from water-saturated soil on the outside could cause basement walls to collapse..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_813">Service damaged septic tanks, cesspools, pits, and leaching systems as soon as possible. Damaged sewage systems are health hazards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_814">Fires, Residential.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_815">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_816">Identify two escape routes from every room and practice using them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_817">In case of fire, get out first; then call for help..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_818">Install smoke alarms on every level of your home and outside each sleeping area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_819">To make your household fire escape plan, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_820">Draw a floor plan of your home; mark two fire escape routes from each room the primary route and the secondary route. In thick, heavy, dark smoke it is easy to become disoriented..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_821">Physically walking through your plan and identifying two escape routes greatly helps everyone understand the best ways to get out safely during a frightening emergency.Be sure the window exits you plan to use can be opened..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_822">Consider getting escape ladders for sleeping areas on the second or third floor. Learn how to use them, and store them near the windows.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_823">If the primary escape routes via stairs are blocked by smoke or fire, the windows may be your only alternative. Escape ladders permit quick exits, reducing time spent in smoke-filled, toxic environments while waiting for firefighters..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_824">Use quick-release devices on barred windows and doors. Security bars without release devices can trap you in a deadly fire. If you have security bars on your windows, be sure one window in each sleeping room has a release device..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_825">If smoke or fire is blocking the primary exit, you must be able to use your secondary routes quickly. Fire deaths have occurred when people were trapped by security bars and were unable to get out and firefighters were unable to get in..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_826">Select a safe outside meeting place for everyone to meet after escaping from a fire. Make sure it will be a safe distance from heat, smoke, and flames. Family members may use different escape routes, exiting on different sides of the home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_827">Gathering in a specific meeting place in front of the home will quickly let you know who is out, and allow you to advise firefighters of who may need help and their probable location inside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_828">Learn the emergency number for reporting a fire. After leaving your home, you will need to call this number from an outside phone or from a neighbor's home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_829">Make sure your house number is easily readable from the street, even at night..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_830">Make sure that street signs in your neighborhood are clear and easy to find..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_831">Practice escaping. With each member of your household in his or her bedroom, press the smoke alarm test button or yell, Fire, several times to alert everyone that they must get out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_832">Each person should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_833">Get out as quickly as possible. If there is smoke on your way out, use your second way out. If you must go through smoke, get low and go under the smoke to your exit..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_834">Practice feeling the doorknob and the space around the door. If it is hot, use your second way out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_835">Close doors after leaving..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_836">Go to the specified meeting place..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_837">Practice getting out of your home during the day and night. Fire can happen at any time. Practicing your routes at night will help you move more quickly should a fire strike in the dark..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_838">When you practice your escape plan, also practice taking your pets with you. Train them to come to you when you call..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_839">Never delay escape or endanger yourself or family to rescue a family pet. However, once you are out of a burning building, stay out and do not return for any pets you may have left behind..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_840">Be sure that everyone in your household knows:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_841">To get out first, and then call for help from outside the burning building, away from toxic smoke and gases..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_842">If a portable phone is handy during your escape, you may take it with you, but do not waste precious time looking for one. Use your neighbor's phone, a cell phone, or nearby pay phone to call for help..; 13 ?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_843">The two escape routes from each room..; 13 ?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_844">The location of the outside meeting place..; 13 ?</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_845">If you cannot get out, stay in a room with the door closed, seal around doors and vents, and open the window for ventilation and to signal to firefighters..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_846">Protect Your Property.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_847">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_848">Take steps to keep fires from starting..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_849">Make sure firefighters can find your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_850">To help prevent fires in your home, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_851">Conduct a fire-hazard hunt in and around your home. Many things around the home can be fire hazards. Taking time to look for and eliminate hazards greatly reduces your risk..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_852">In your hazard hunt, include your barns, out buildings, or any other structures that house animals. Invite your local fire department to examine your barns and out buildings and give you suggestions..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_853">If you smoke, choose fire safe cigarettes. They are less likely to cause fires. Encourage smokers to smoke outside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_854">Avoid smoking in bed, or when drowsy or medicated. Bed linens are highly combustible. It is easier to be burned, and highly likely individuals will suffer severe burns, when fires start in beds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_855">Drowsy or medicated people may forget lit materials, resulting in fire. Never allow smoking in a home where oxygen is in use..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_856">Provide smokers with deep, sturdy ashtrays. Douse cigarette and cigar butts with water before disposal. Smoking materials are the leading cause of residential fire deaths in the United States..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_857">Keep matches and lighters up high, away from children, preferably in a locked cabinet. Children are fascinated by fire and may play with matches and lighters if they are not kept out of reach..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_858">Make sure your home heating sources are clean and in working order. Many home fires are started by poorly maintained furnaces or stoves, cracked or rusted furnace parts, or chimneys with creosote buildup..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_859">Be sure all portable and fixed space heaters have been certified by an independent testing laboratory. Keep blankets, clothing, curtains, furniture, and anything that could get hot and catch fire at least three feet away from all heat sources..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_860">Plug heaters directly into the wall socket rather than using an extension cord and unplug them when they are not in use or occupants go to bed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_861">Use kerosene heaters only if permitted by law in your area. Refuel kerosene heaters only outdoors and after they have cooled. Kerosene has a low flash point. If mistakenly dripped on hot surfaces, it can cause fires..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_862">Do not substitute gasoline for kerosene in the heater..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_863">Have chimneys and wood stoves inspected annually and cleaned if necessary. Chimneys and wood stoves build up creosote, which is the residue left behind by burning wood..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_864">Creosote is flammable and needs to be professionally removed periodically. Store ashes in a metal container with a tight-fitting lid..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_865">Keep the stove area clean and clear of combustibles, such as towels, clothing, curtains,bags, boxes, and other appliances. Combustible materials near stoves may catch fire quickly when your attention is elsewhere..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_866">Wear short or restrained sleeves when cooking. Loose sleeves can catch fire quickly if dragged across a hot burner..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_867">If you are cooking and a fire starts in a pan, slide a lid over the burning pan and turn off the burner. Leave the lid in place until the pan is completely cool. Using a lid to contain and smother the fire is your safest action..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_868">Getting the fire extinguisher or baking soda to extinguish the fire delays action. Flour and other cooking products can react explosively to flame and should never be sprinkled over fire. Moving the pan can cause serious injury or spread the fire..; 13 ? 94</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_869">Never pour water on grease fires..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_870">If you try to use a fire extinguisher on a fire and the fire does not immediately die down, drop the extinguisher and get out. Most portable extinguishers empty in as little as 8 to 10 seconds..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_871">Use only flashlights when the power is out, not candles..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_872">Never leave a burning candle unattended, even for a minute..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_873">Check electrical wiring in your home. Fix or replace frayed extension cords, exposed wires, or loose plugs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_874">Make sure wiring is not under rugs, attached by nails, or in high traffic areas..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_875">Make sure electrical outlets have cover plates and no exposed wiring..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_876">Avoid overloading outlets or extension cords..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_877">Purchase only appliances and electrical devices that bear the label of an independent testing laboratory..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_878">Buy only heaters certified for safety by an independent testing laboratory and follow the manufacturer's directions. Heaters that have gone through rigorous testing and are approved for use in the home are less likely to cause fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_879">Store combustible materials in open areas away from heat sources..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_880">Place rags used to apply flammable household chemicals in metal containers with tight-fitting lids..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_881">Install a carbon monoxide alarm in a central location outside each separate sleeping area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_882">What to Do if a Fire Starts.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_883">In case of fire, alert others and get out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_884">Once out, call the fire department and stay out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_885">If you cannot get out, stay in a closed room, ventilate the room, and signal to firefighters..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_886">If a fire starts in your home or you hear the smoke alarm, remain calm, and carry out your escape plan, as you have practiced. You should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_887">Yell "Fire!" several times and go outside right away. Smoke alarms go off because there is enough smoke and toxic gas to cause harm. Yell to let people know the emergency is real, and they should get out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_888">If you live in a building with elevators, use the stairs. Never try to hide from fire. Leave all your things where they are and save yourself..; 13 50/51</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_889">If your escape route is filled with smoke, use your second way out. It is very hard to find your way through thick, heavy smoke. Using your second way out will provide a safer alternative..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_890">If you must escape through smoke, get low and go under the smoke to your exit. Fires produce many poisonous gases. Some are heavy and will sink low to the floor; others will rise, carrying soot toward the ceiling. Close doors behind you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_891">If you are escaping through a closed door, feel the doorknob and the space around the door before opening the door. If it is cool and there is no smoke at the bottom or top, open the door slowly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_892">If you see smoke or fire in your exit path, close the door and use your second way out. If the doorknob or the space around the door is hot, use your second way out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_893">It is a natural tendency to automatically use the door, but fire may be right outside. Feeling the doorknob and the space around the door will warn you of possible danger..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_894">If smoke, heat, or flames block your exit routes and you cannot get outside safely, stay in the room with the door closed. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_895">Open the window a few inches at the top and bottom for ventilation, turn on a light, and hang a light-colored object outside the window to alert firefighters to your presence. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_896">Hang anything white or light-colored you can find the bigger the betterfor example, a sheet, shirt, jacket, window shade or blind, or poster with the white back facing out..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_897">If there is a phone in the room, call the fire department and tell where you are. Seal around doors and vents with duct tape, towels, or sheets to help slow the entry of deadly smoke into the room..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_898">Wait by the window for help. The first thing firefighters will do when they arrive at a fire is check for trapped persons. Hanging a sheet out lets them know where to find you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_899">Get out as safely and quickly as you can. The less time you are exposed to poisonous gases, heat, or flames, the safer you will be..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_900">Once you are outside, go to your meeting place and then send one person to call the fire department. Everyone in the household should know where the outside meeting place is and should go directly to this meeting place in case of a fire and stay there..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_901">Gathering in a specific outside location in front of the home will quickly let you know who is outside, and allow you to advise firefighters of who may need help and their probable location inside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_902">Once you are out, stay out. Children as well as adults are often concerned about the safety of their pets, so discuss and plan for this before a fire starts. The safest option is for pets to sleep in the room of a family member..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_903">If escape is needed, grab your pet on the way out, but only if you can do this without delaying and endangering yourself or family members..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_904">Many people are overcome by smoke and poisonous gases while trying to rescue others, pets, or possessions. No one should go into a burning or smoking building except a trained fire fighter who has the proper breathing apparatus and protective clothing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_905">What to Do If Your Clothes Catch on Fire.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_906">If your clothes are on fire, stop, drop,and roll..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_907">Do not run..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_908">If your clothes catch on fire, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_909">Stop what you are doing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_910">Drop to the ground and cover your face if you can..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_911">Roll over and over or back and forth until the flames go out. Running will only make the fire burn faster. Practicing can help you respond properly and more quickly in an actual emergency situation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_912">Once the flames are out, cool the burned skin with water for three to five minutes. Call for medical attention..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_913">What to Do After a Fire.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_914">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_915">Protect yourself..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_916">Protect your property..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_917">Give first aid where needed. After calling 9-1-1 or your local emergency number, cool and cover burns to reduce the chance of further injury or infection. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_918">People and animals that are seriously injured or burned should be transported to professional medical or veterinary help immediately..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_919">Stay out of fire-damaged homes until local fire authorities say it is safe to re-enter. Fire may have caused damage that could injure you or your family. There may be residual smoke or gases that are unsafe to breathe..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_920">Look for structural damage. Fire authorities may allow you to re-enter, but they may not have completed a thorough inspection. Look for damage that will need repair..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_921">Check that all wiring and utilities are safe. Fire may cause damage to inside walls and utility lines not normally visible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_922">Discard food that has been exposed to heat, smoke, or soot. The high temperatures of fire and its by-products can make food unsafe..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_923">Wildland Fire.;.;.;.;;</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_924">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_925">Determine your risk..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_926">Make your home easy to find and easy to access..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_927">Identify and maintain outside watersources..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_928">If you are at risk for wildland fire, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_929">Talk with members of your household about wildland fires how to help prevent them and what to do if one occurs..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_930">Make sure that fire vehicles can get to your home by clearly marking all drive way entrances and displaying your address number..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_931">Make sure the drive way is wide enough to allow fire emergency vehicles easy access to the home with ample turnaround space. Keep the driveway in good condition..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_932">Post fire emergency telephone numbers by every phone in your home. In a wildland fire, every second counts..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_933">Plan and practice two ways out of your neighborhood. Your primary route may be blocked; know another way out just in case. (See Evacuation and Sheltering, and PostdisasterSafety in the appendix.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_934">Identify and maintain an adequate water source outside your home, such as a smallpond, cistern, well, swimming pool, or hydrant. Keep a garden hose that is long enough to reach any area of the home and other structures on the property..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_935">Install freeze-proof exterior water outlets on at least two sides of the home and near other structures on the property. Install additional outlets at least 50 feet (15 meters) from the home. Firefighters may be able to use them..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_936">Keep handy household items that can be used as fire tools: a rake, ax, hand saw orchain saw, bucket, and shovel. You may need to fight small fires before emergency responders arrive. Having this equipment will make your efforts more effective..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_937">Develop a wildland fire-specific evacuation plan and coordinate it with your Family Disaster Plan..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_938">If you live in an area at risk for wildland fire, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_939">Create safety zones to separate your home and out buildings, such as barns, from plants and vegetation. (Consult your local fire department for recommendations about the safety zones for your property.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_940">Maintain the greatest distance possible between your home and materials that may burn in a wildland fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_941">Within this area, you can take steps to reduce potential exposure to flames and radiant heat. Swimming pools and patios can help define safety zones..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_942">If your home sits on a steep slope, standard protective measures may not suffice. Fire moves quickly up steep slopes. A larger safety zone may be necessary. Stone walls can act as heat shields and deflect flames along a ridge..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_943">Regularly clean roofs and gutters. Remove all dead limbs, needles, and debris that spread fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_944">Equip chimneys and stove pipes with a spark arrester that meets the requirements of National Fire Protection Association Standard 211. (Contact your local fire departmentfor exact specifications.). This will reduce the chance of burning cinders escaping through the chimney, starting outdoor fires..;</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_945">Have a fire extinguisher ( A-B-C rated) and get training from the fire department in how to use it. Different extinguishers operate in different ways. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_946">A water extinguisher is better for vegetation fires and to raise the moisture level in leaves and grasses. Unless you know how to use your extinguisher, you may not be able to use it effectively. There is no time to read directions during an emergency..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_947">Consider installing protective shutters or multi paned windows. The extreme heat created by the fire causes single paned windows to break, permitting burning cindersand superheated air to enter and ignite the interior of the building. The right shutters can reduce the potential for these cinders to cause your home to burn..; .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_948">Keep a ladder handy that will reach the roof. You may need to get on the roof toremove combustible debris..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_949">Clear all combustible vegetation and remove wooden lawn furniture to reduce the fuel load. Rake away leaves. Remove leaves, rubbish, dead limbs, and twigs from understructures and dispose of them properly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_950">Have a professional tree service create a 15-foot (5-meter) space between tree crowns, and remove limbs within 6 to 10 feet (2 to 3meters) of the ground. This will help reduce the chance of fire spreading from tree to treeor from ground to tree..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_951">Remove dead branches from all trees. Dead branches are very combustible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_952">Keep trees adjacent to buildings free of dead or dying wood and moss..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_953">Remove tree branches and shrubs within 10 feet (3 meters) of a stovepipe orchimney outlet..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_954">If you have horses or livestock, be sure to sweep hay and other burnable feed away from the building that houses the animals. Close windows and doors to prevent embersfrom entering stables..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_955">Keep all tree and shrub limbs trimmed so they do not come in contact with electrical wires. Electrical wires can be easily damaged or knocked loose by swayingbranches..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_956">Remove vines from the walls of your home. Even live vines can spread fire quickly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_957">Mow and water grass regularly. This will help reduce the fuel available for fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_958">Place above ground propane tanks at least 30 feet (9 meters) from the home or other structures. Refer to NFPA 58: Liquefied Petroleum Gas Code for specific distances based on tank size..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_959">Clear a 10-foot (3-meter) area around propane tanks and the barbecue. Place ametal screen over the grill. Use non combustible screen material with mesh no coarser than one-quarter inch..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_960">Place stove, fireplace, and grill ashes in a metal bucket, soak in water for two days,then bury the cold ashes in mineral soil. Fires can start quickly from hidden cinders orburnt materials that are still hot..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_961">Once they are burned, chunks of flammable items can ignite at lower temperatures. Bury ashes to avoid potential fires..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_962">Stack firewood at least 30 feet (9 meters) away and uphill from your home. Clear combustible material within 20 feet (6 meters) of the stack. Fire tends to travel uphill, so keep highly combustible firewood and other materials above your home..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_963">Use only wood-burning devices that are listed by UL or other certification laboratories and approved by your local fire department..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_964">Box eaves to prevent sparks from entering the structure under the roof line..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_965">Place metal screens over openings to prevent collection of litter. Cover openings to windows, floors, roof, and attic with metal screen (not vinyl). Use at least quarter-inchscreen beneath porches, decks, floors, and the home itself. Eighth-inch mesh screen is better. Litter, such as leaves, branches, twigs, and loose papers, quickly increases thefuel available for a fire..; .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_966">Avoid open burning completely, especially during the fire season. Ash and cinders can float in the air, and they may be blown into areas with heavy fuel load and start wildland fires. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_967">Check with your local fire department for burning regulations and permits. Report hazardous conditions that could cause a wildland fire. Community responders may be able to eliminate or reduce conditions that could cause fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_968">What to Do When Wildland Fire Threatens.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_969">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_970">Keep informed..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_971">Get ready to leave at a moment s notice. The earlier a person leaves, the safer they will be..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_972">If you have time, take steps to protect.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_973">If there are reports of wildland fires, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_974">Listen regularly to local radio or television stations for updated emergency information. Follow the instructions of local officials. Local officials will be able to adviseyou of the safest escape route, which may be different than you expect..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_975">Wildland fires can change direction and speed suddenly. In addition to listening to radio and televisionreports, go outside to look at the fire from time to time..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_976">If you believe the fire is too close to your location, evacuate immediately. The fire may move too fast for officials to issuee vacuation notifications..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_977">Back your car into the garage or park it in an open space facing the direction of escape. Shut the car doors and roll up the windows. Leave the key in the ignition. Closegarage windows and doors. Remove all obstacles to a quick escape..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_978">Confine pets to one room. Make plans to care for your pets in case you must evacuate. Pets may try to run if they feel threatened by fire. Keeping them inside and inone room will allow you to find them quickly if you need to leave..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_979">If you think an evacuation may be advised, and if you have large, unusual, or numerous animals, start evacuating them out of harm s way as soon as you are aware of impending danger..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_980">If you are using a horse or other trailer to evacuate your animals, move early rather than wait until it may be too late to maneuver a trailer through slow traffic and thick smoke..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_981">Arrange temporary housing at a friend s or relative's home outside the threatened area. You will be more comfortable in someone's home than in a public shelter. Plus,many shelters do not allow pets..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_982">If you are sure you have time, take steps to reduce the chance of your home catching fire or lessen the amount of damage from a nearby fire:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_983">Shut off gas at the meter only if advised to do so by local officials on the radio or television..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_984">If you have a propane tank system, turn off the valves on the system, and leave the valves closed until the propane supplier inspects your system..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_985">Open fireplace dampers. Close fireplace screens. Burning embers will not be sucked down into a home from the outside..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_986">Moreover, if a spark arrestor is used on the chimney to prevent embers from getting out, it will also prevent embers from getting in..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_987">Close windows, vents, doors, blinds, or non combustible window coverings, and heavy drapes. Remove light weight drapes and curtains..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_988">Move combustible furniture into the center of the home away from windows and sliding-glass doors..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_989">Close all doors and windows inside your home to prevent draft..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_990">Place valuables that will not be damaged by water in a pool or pond..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_991">Place sprinklers up to 50 feet (15 meters) away from the structures to raise the moisture level of nearby vegetation..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_992">Seal attic and ground vents with precut plywood or commercial seals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_993">Remove combustible items from around the home, lawn, and pool sidefurniture, umbrellas, tarp coverings, firewood..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_994">Connect the garden hose to outside taps..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_995">Gather fire tools (shovels, hoes, hoses)..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_996">Note: In the unlikely event that you choose not to evacuate,make sure all fire tools are outside and easy to access,including hoses in the front and back yards..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_997">Be aware that water pressure will probably decrease because of the heavy demand for firefighting, or water may not be available at allbecause electric pumps have failed or water reservoirs aredrained..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_998">What to Do if You Must Evacuate.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_999">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1000">Leave as early as possible..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1001">Prepare your home if you have time..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1002">If you think you should or if authorities tell you to evacuate immediately, go right away; delay could be deadly..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1003">If advised to evacuate immediately, do so immediately. You may have only minutes to act. Save yourself and those with you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1004">If advised to evacuate as soon as possible, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1005">Wear protective clothing sturdy shoes, cotton or wool long pants and long-sleeved shirt, and gloves. Bring a handkerchief to protect your face. Hot embers or cinders canburn your skin if you come in contact with them. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1006">Smoke can make it difficult to breathe and damage breathing passages..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1007">Prepare your home and leave early. If you wait until the last minute, you place yourself at risk and also interfere with fire department response..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1008">Take your Disaster Supplies Kit in which you have placed prescription medications for household members, as well as copies of essential papers and identification items. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1009">Also,if time permits, load your vehicle with other essential items that could not be replaced if they were destroyed by fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1010">Take your pets and your pet disaster supplies with you..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1011">Lock your home. There may be others who evacuate after you or return before you.Secure your home as you normally would..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1012">Call the out-of-town contact you chose when creating your Family Disaster Plan and tell him or her what has happened and where you are going..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1013">Choose a route away from the fire. Watch for changes in the speed and direction offire and smoke. Staying as far away as possible will provide you with the greatest safety..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1014">Continue to listen to a local radio or television station for evacuation information..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1015">If you are trapped, crouch in a pond, river, or pool. Do not put wet clothing or bandanas over your nose or mouth because moist air causes more damage to airways than dry air at the same temperature..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1016">If there is no body of water, look for shelter in a cleared area or among a bed of rocks. Lie flat, face down, and cover your body with soil. Breathe the air close to the ground to avoid scorching your lungs or inhaling smoke..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1017">You cannot outrun a fire. Wildland fires move very fast and create their own wind, helping them to move even faster and burn even hotter..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1018">What to Do When You Are Allowed to Return After a Wildland Fire.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1019">CORE ACTION MESSAGES.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1020">Get permission from fire officials before entering a burned wildland area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1021">Look out for hazards, such as fallen wires and poles and ash pits..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1022">Look out as burned trees can fall because of weakened roots..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1023">Be alert to the possibility of re-ignition..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1024">Take precautions while cleaning up.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1025">When you return to your home after a wildland fire, you should:.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1026">Obtain permission from officials before entering a burned wildland area..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1027">Use caution and exercise good judgment when re-entering a burned wildland area. Hazards may still exist, including hot spots, which can flare up without warning..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1028">Avoid damaged or fallen power poles or lines, and downed wires. Immediately report electrical damage to authorities. Electric wires may shock people or cause furtherfires..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1029">If you come across dangerous wires, if possible, remain on the scene to warn others of the hazard until a repair crew arrives..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1030">Watch for ash pits and mark them for safety. Ash pits are holes full of hot ashes created by burned trees and stumps. You can be seriously burned by falling into an ashpit or landing on one with your hands or feet. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1031">Warn your family and neighbors to keep clear of the pits..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1032">Watch animals closely..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1033">Keep all your animals under your direct control. Hidden embers and hot spots could burn your pets paws or hooves..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1034">Pets may become disoriented, particularly because fire often affects scentmarkers that normally allow them to find their homes..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1035">Your pets may be able to escape from your home or through a broken fence..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1036">In addition, the behavior of pets may change dramatically after a fire, becoming aggressive or defensive, so be aware of their well-being and take measures to protect them from hazards, including displaced wild animals, and to ensure the safety of other people and animals..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1037">If there is no power, check to make sure the main breaker is on. Fires may causebreakers to trip. If the breakers are on and power is still not present, contact the utility company..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1038">Debris should be wetted down to minimize health impacts from breathing dust particles..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1039">Use a two-strap dust particulate mask with nose clip and coveralls for protection..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1040">Wear leather gloves and heavy-soled shoes to protect hands and feet fromsharp objects while removing debris..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1041">Wear rubber gloves when working with outhouse remnants, plumbing fixtures,and sewer piping. They can contain high levels of bacteria..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1042">Hazardous materials such as kitchen and bathroom cleaning products, paint, batteries, contaminated fuel, and damaged fuel containers need to be properly handled to avoid risk..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1043">Check with local authorities for hazardous disposal assistance.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1044">If you turned off the valves on a propane tank system, contact the propane supplier,and leave the valves closed until the supplier inspects your system..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1045">Tanks, brass and copper fittings, and lines may have been damaged by the heat and be unsafe. If fire burned the tank, the pressure relief valve probably opened and released the contents..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1046">If you have a heating oil tank system, contact a heating oil supplier for an inspection of your system before using it..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1047">An outside tank may have shifted or fallen from the stand and fuel lines may have kinked or weakened. Heat from the fire may have caused thetank to warp or bulge..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1048">Nonvented tanks are more likely to bulge or show signs of stress. The fire may have loosened or damaged fittings and filters..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1049">Be careful around burned trees and power poles.. Any tree or power pole that has been weakened by fire may be a hazard. Winds are normally responsible for toppling weakened trees and poles..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1050">The wind patterns in your area may have changed as a result of the loss of adjacent tree cover..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1051">Look for burns on the tree trunk. If the bark on the trunk has been burned off or scorched by very high temperatures completely around the circumference, the tree will not survive. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1052">If fire has burned deep into the trunk, the tree should be considered unstable..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1053">Look for burned roots by probing the ground with a rod around the base of thetree and several feet away from the base. Roots are generally six to eight inches(15 to 20 centimeters) below the surface..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1054">If the roots have been burned, the treecould be toppled by wind..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1055">A scorched tree is one that has lost part or all of its leaves or needles. Healthy deciduous trees are resilient and may produce new branches and leaves as well as sprouts at the base of the tree..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1056">Evergreen trees may survive when partially scorched. An evergreen tree that has been damaged by fire is subject to bark beetle attack. Seek professional assistance from the state forestry office concerning measures for protecting evergreens from bark beetle attack..;;</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1057">Discard food that has been exposed to heat, smoke, or soot. The high temperaturesof fire and its by-products can make food unsafe. (See Appendix: Food and Water Exposed to Floodwater, Fire, and Chemicals.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1058">If you are in doubt about the safety of your water, contact local public health officials. Wells at undamaged homes should be safe, unless affected by a fuel spill..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1059">If you use water from a public well, have a water sample collected and tested before consuming it. Water may have been contaminated with bacteria due to a loss of waterpressure in the plumbing..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1060">Stay out of a canyon below a burned hill or mountain if there is even a chance of rain. .</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1061">Such canyons are dangerous if it has rained heavily recently, if it is currently raining in the canyon, or if it is raining or could rain in the hills or mountains above the canyon..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1062">Risks for mudslides and debris flows are high in such burned areas for three to five years after a wildland fire..</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1063">Smoke Alarms.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1064">If you have a fire, smoke alarms can cut nearly in half your risk of dying in a fire. Smoke alarms sense abnormal amounts of smoke or invisible combustion gases in the air. They can detect both smoldering and flaming fires. National Fire Protection Association 72, the National Fire Alarm Code, now requires in new homes hard-wired, interconnected smoke alarms with battery back-up on every level of the home, outside each sleeping area, and inside each bedroom. It also requires that alarms be wired together so that if one sounds, they all sound.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1065">If smoke alarms are not already in place, at a minimum install them on every level of the home and outside each sleeping area. If a fire occurs inside a bedroom, dangerous gases can cause heavier sleep. For the best protection, install interconnected smoke alarms in each bedroom and throughout the home. When one sounds, they all sound.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1066">To prevent nuisance alarms, vacuum cobwebs and dust from your smoke alarms monthly. Never disable a smoke alarm, even if you experience nuisance alarms while cooking or showering. Clean the smoke alarm following the manufacturer’s instructions and, if possible, relocate it away from the kitchen or bathroom. If nuisance alarms are a persistent problem, look for a different type of smoke alarm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1067">Use the test button to test your smoke alarms at least monthly. The test feature tests all electronic functions and is safer than testing with a controlled fire (matches, lighters, cigarettes). If the smoke alarm manufacturer's instructions permit the use of an aerosol smoke product for testing the smoke alarm, and you prefer that method, choose one that has been listed (examined and tested to appropriate product safety standards) by a third-party product testing laboratory, and use it in accordance with the product instructions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1068">If you have battery-powered smoke alarms, replace the batteries at least once a year. (Replace the batteries in your carbon monoxide (CO) alarms at the same time you replace your smoke alarm batteries.) Some agencies recommend that you replace batteries when the time changes from standard to daylight savings each spring and then back again in the fall. "Change your clock, change your batteries." Replacing batteries this often certainly will not hurt; however, data show that fresh batteries will last at least a year, so more frequent replacement is not necessary unless the smoke alarm begins to chirp. Also, Arizona, Hawaii, the eastern portion of Indiana, Puerto Rico, American Samoa, and Guam do not use daylight savings time. Pick an easy-to-remember anniversary, such as your birthday or a national holiday, as the day to change the batteries each year.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1069">Replace your smoke alarms every 10 years. This is the recommendation of the National Fire Protection Association and the U.S. Consumer Product Safety Commission. Smoke alarms become less sensitive over time.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1070">Be sure to install smoke alarms in areas where pets are and in other buildings that house animals where humans can hear them.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1071">Carbon Monoxide Alarms.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1072">Every home should have properly installed and maintained carbon monoxide (CO) alarms. CO alarms can help detect CO, a colorless, odorless gas produced by burning any fuel. Exposure to high levels of CO can cause death. The initial symptoms of CO poisoning are similar to the flu and include dizziness, fatigue, headache, nausea, and irregular breathing.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1073">Install battery-operated CO alarms or plug-in CO alarms with battery back-up in your home, according to the manufacturer’s installation instructions. CO alarms should be certified to the requirements of the latest safety standards for CO alarms (UL 2034, IAS 6-96, or CSA 6.19.01). It is especially important to have a CO alarm near sleeping areas.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1074">Test and maintain your CO alarms according to the manufacturer’s instructions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1075">If your carbon monoxide (CO) alarm sounds, immediately move to a fresh air location and call for help. Remain in the fresh air location until emergency personnel say it is ok.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1076">Because of the risk of CO poisoning, never operate unvented fuel-burning appliances in any closed room or where people or animals are sleeping. CO poisoning from fuel-burning appliances kills people in the United States each year.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1077">CO can leak from faulty furnaces or fuel-fired heaters or can be trapped inside a home by a blocked chimney or flue. Burning charcoal inside a home produces CO. Running an automobile engine in an attached garage can cause CO to enter a home and so can running a portable generator if it is near windows, doors, or vents, even if it is outdoors.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1078">Never use gas appliances such as ranges, ovens, or clothes dryers for heating your home. Never use a portable generator in an enclosed or partially enclosed space, including in your home or in a garage, basement, crawl space, or other partially enclosed area, even with ventilation. Locate a generator outdoors and away from doors, windows, and vents that could allow CO to come indoors. Generators can produce high levels of deadly CO very quickly. (See Appendix: Portable Generators.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1079">Fire Extinguishers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1080">Consider having one or more working fire extinguishers in your home. An extinguisher rated “A-B-C” is recommended for home use. Many fire extinguisher models are designed for one-time use and cannot be recharged.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1081">Get training from the fire department or a fire extinguisher manufacturer on how to use your fire extinguisher. Fire extinguishers from various manufacturers operate in different ways. Unless you know how to use your extinguisher, you may not be able to use it effectively, or it could place you in greater danger. There is no time to read directions during an emergency. Only adults should handle and use extinguishers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1082">Install extinguishers high on the wall, near an exit, and away from heat sources. Extinguishers should be easily accessible to adults trained to use them, and kept away from children's curious hands. Heat may make the contents less effective or cause the extinguisher to lose its charge more quickly.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1083">If you try to use a fire extinguisher on a fire and the fire does not immediately die down, drop the extinguisher and get out. Most portable extinguishers empty in 8 seconds.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1084">Look at your fire extinguisher to ensure that it is properly charged. Fire extinguishers will not work properly if they are not properly charged. Use the gauge or test button to check that there is proper pressure. Follow the manufacturer's instructions for replacing or recharging fire extinguishers. If the unit is low on pressure, damaged, or corroded, replace it or have it professionally serviced.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1085">Before you begin to fight a fire with a fire extinguisher, be sure that:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1086">Everyone has left or is leaving the home.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1087">The fire department has been called.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1088">The fire is small and not spreading.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1089">Your back is to an exit you can use quickly.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1090">There is not much smoke in the room.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1091">Arc-Fault Circuit Interrupters (AFCIs).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1092">Consider installing AFCIs in your home’s electrical panel box. Problems in home wiring, like arcing and sparking, are associated with more then 40,000 home fires each year. The Consumer Product Safety Commissions reports that these fires claim over 350 lives and injure 1400 victims annually. An arc-fault circuit interrupter (AFCI) is provides enhanced protection from fires resulting from these unsafe home wiring conditions. They detect abnormal arcing in a circuit (which can cause overheating and lead to an electrical fire) and de-energize the circuit when an arc fault is detected. AFCIs are recognized for their effectiveness and now required by the National Electric Code® for bedroom circuits in new construction. Older homes with ordinary circuit breakers especially may benefit from the added protection against the arcing faults that can occur in aging wire systems. Be certain to have a qualified electrician install AFCIs. This installation involved working within electrical panel boxes that are usually live; even with the main circuit breakers turned off.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1093">AFCIs should not be confused with ground-fault circuit interrupters (GFCI). While both AFCIs and GFCIs are important safety devices, they have different functions. The popular GFCI devices are designed to protect people against severe or fatal electric shock, not fire hazards. GFCIs can protect against some electrical fires by detecting faults to ground but cannot detect hazardous “across-the-line” arcing faults that can cause fires. The National Electric Code® requires GFCI protection for receptacles located outdoors, in bathrooms, garages, kitchens, crawl spaces and unfinished basements; and at certain locations such as near swimming pools.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1094">Home Fire Sprinkler Systems.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1095">Consider installing an automatic fire sprinkler system in your home. Although smoke alarms are essential in every household, they are designed to detect, not control, a fire. Home fire sprinklers complement the alarms' work, providing a way to fight flames immediately. In less time than it would take the fire department to arrive on the scene, home fire sprinklers can prevent a fire from spreading and even extinguish a fire. A sprinkler system can decrease the chance that deadly smoke and gases will reach your family. In addition, sprinkler systems can put out fire when you are away from home, and if they are connected to an alarm system, may notify the fire department in your absence.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1096">To ensure sprinkler system reliability, be sure to use a qualified installer who adheres to National Fire Protection Association (NFPA) codes and standards and local fire safety regulations.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1097">Portable Generators.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1098">Portable generators are useful when temporary or remote electric power is needed, but they also can be hazardous. The primary hazards to avoid when using a generator are carbon monoxide (CO) poisoning from the toxic engine exhaust, electric shock or electrocution, and fire. Every year, people die in incidents related to portable generator use.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1099">Carbon Monoxide Hazard:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1100">Never use a portable generator in an enclosed or partially enclosed space. Portable generators can produce high levels of CO very quickly. When you use a portable generator, remember that you cannot smell or see CO. Even if you cannot smell exhaust fumes, you may still be exposed to CO. If you start to feel sick, dizzy, or weak while using a portable generator, get to fresh air right away. Alert others in the home or in the vicinity to get to fresh air. Do not delay. The CO from portable generators can rapidly lead to full incapacitation and death.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1101">If you experience serious symptoms, get medical attention immediately. Inform medical staff that CO poisoning is suspected. If you experienced symptoms while indoors, have someone call the fire department to determine when it is safe to reenter the building.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1102">Follow these safety tips to protect against CO poisoning:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1103">Never use a portable generator indoors, including in homes, garages, basements, crawl spaces, and other enclosed or partially enclosed areas, even with ventilation. Opening doors and windows or using fans will not prevent CO buildup.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1104">Follow the instructions that come with your portable generator. Locate the unit outdoors and away from doors, windows, and vents that could allow CO to come indoors.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1105">Install battery-operated CO alarms or plug-in CO alarms with battery back-up in your home, according to the manufacturer’s installation instructions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1106">Electrical Hazards.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1107">Follow these tips to protect against electrical hazards:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1108">Keep the portable generator dry and do not use it where it could get wet by rain or snow. To protect it from moisture, operate it on a dry surface under an open, canopy-like structure. Dry your hands if they are wet before touching the generator.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1109">Plug appliances directly into the portable generator. Or, use a heavy-duty, outdoor-rated extension cord that is rated (in watts or amps) at least equal to the sum of the connected appliance loads. Check that the entire cord is free of cuts or tears and that the plug has all three prongs, especially a grounding pin.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1110">Never try to power the home wiring by plugging the portable generator into a wall outlet, a practice known as “backfeeding” This is an extremely dangerous practice that presents an electrocution risk to utility workers and neighbors served by the same utility transformer. It also bypasses some of the built-in household circuit protection devices.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1111">If you must connect a portable generator to the home wiring to power appliances, have a qualified electrician install the appropriate equipment in accordance with local electrical codes. Or, check with your utility company to see if it can install an appropriate power transfer switch.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1112">For power outages, permanently installed stationary generators are better suited for providing backup power to a home. Even a properly connected portable generator can become overloaded. This may result in overheating or stressing the generator components, possibly leading to a generator failure.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1113">Fire Hazards.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1114">Follow these tips to protect against fire hazards:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1115">Never store fuel for your portable generator in the home. Gasoline, propane, kerosene, and other flammable liquids should be stored outside of living areas in properly labeled, non-glass, safety containers. Do not store them near a fuel-burning appliance, such as a natural gas water heater in a garage. If the fuel is spilled or the container is not sealed properly, invisible vapors from the fuel can travel along the ground and can be ignited by the appliance’s pilot light or by arcs from electric switches in the appliance.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1116">Before refueling a portable generator, turn it off and let it cool down. Gasoline spilled on hot engine parts could ignite.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1117">Tips for Preparing Your Disaster Supplies Kits.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1118">Keep items in separate airtight plastic bags. This will help protect them from damage or spoiling.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1119">Observe the expiration or “use by” date on stored food and water. If you have prepared you own containers of water, replace them every six months to ensure freshness.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1120">Rethink your kit and family needs at least once a year. Replace batteries, update medicines, clothes, etc.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1121">Ask your physician or pharmacist about storing prescription medications. You may find that the best solution is to gradually acquire a reserve by refilling prescriptions a little early, but always using those on hand first to avoid having the expiration dates lapse. Be sure they are stored to meet instructions on the label. It may be difficult to obtain prescription medications during a disaster because stores may be closed or supplies may be limited. Keep copies of essential prescriptions with you at all times.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1122">Use easy-to-carry containers for the supplies you would most likely need for an evacuation. Label them clearly. Think about using:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1123">Large trash container with handles and a cover</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1124">Camping backpack</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1125">Duffel bag</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1126">Cargo container that fits on the roof of your vehicle</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1127">Insulated cooler that protects stored items in hot climates</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1128">Store water separately to prevent damage from leakage.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1129">Always keep your cell phone with you, if you have one. Do not pack it in the kit. Consider getting an extra cell phone battery to keep with your Disaster Supplies Kit.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1130">Emergency Supplies for Your Vehicle.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1131">In addition to the basic vehicle safety items—properly inflated spare tire, wheel wrench, and jack—you should also keep a smaller version of your disaster supplies kit (see Disaster Supplies Kit) and a first aid kit (see Appendix: First Aid Kit) in your vehicle. Include local maps where you drive, basic tools (pliers, adjustable wrench, screwdriver, etc.), flashlight and extra batteries, duct tape, reflective triangle, signal flares, a roll of quarters for making phone calls and vending machines, and essential fluids (oil, coolant and transmission fluid). Rags are helpful to wipe up fluid or cleaning grime off your hands. You may also consider having a fire extinguisher, jumper cables, bottled water, nonperishable food, medications, toilet tissue and premoistened towelettes in case you breakdown or are stuck. Check your vehicle supplies regularly for expired or unusable items.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1132">When driving in winter or cold climates, add a windshield scraper, snow brush, salt, sand, shovel, tire chains and warm clothing. Blankets or sleeping bags will keep you</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1133">warm and can also be used to cover the ground if you need to get near the ground to make repairs or change a tire. Extra socks and shoes are helpful if your feet get wet or you are wearing non-waterproof shoes.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1134">First Aid Kit Contents.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1135">*ACFAS MINIMUM RECOMMENDED FAMILY KIT CONTENTS</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1136">Assemble a first aid kit to include in your Disaster Supplies Kit and one for each vehicle.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1137">Include:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1138">Additional items may be added to personalize or customize this kit.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1139">Family First Aid Kit Content Suggested Use</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1140">Absorbent Compress 5x9 dressing Cover and protect open wounds</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1141">Adhesive Bandages (Assorted Sizes) Cover and protect open wounds</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1142">Adhesive Tape (cloth) 1” To secure bandages or splints</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1143">Antibiotic Ointment packets (approx 1 g) Anti-infection</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1144">Antiseptic wipe Packets Wound cleaning/germ killer</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1145">Aspirin (Chewable) 81 mg For symptoms of a heart attack**</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1146">Blanket (Space Blanket) Maintain body temperature for shock</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1147">CPR Breathing Barrier (w/one-way valve) Protection during rescue breathing or CPR</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1148">Instant Cold Compress To control swelling</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1149">Gloves (large), disposable, non-latex Prevent body fluid contact</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1150">Hydrocortisone Ointment Packets (approx 1 g) External rash treatment</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1151">Scissors Cut tape, cloth,or bandages</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1152">Roller Bandage 3” (individually wrapped) Secure wound dressing in place</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1153">Roller Bandage 4” (individually wrapped) Secure wound dressing in place</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1154">Sterile Gauze Pad 3x3 To control external bleeding</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1155">Sterile Gauze Pad 4x4 To control external bleeding</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1156">Thermometer, Oral (Non-Mercury/Non-Glass) Take temperature orally</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1157">Triangular Bandage Sling or binder/splinting</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1158">Tweezers Remove splinters or ticks</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1159">First Aid Instruction booklet Self explanatory</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1160">*ACFAS is the American National Red Cross Advisory Council on First Aid and Safety</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1161">Note: Remember to include prescription drugs in a Disaster Supplies Kit. Because the storage requirements of prescription drugs vary, some may have to be added to the kit at the last minute. You may want to pin or tape a note to the outside of your kit container reminding you to take along prescription drugs if you have to evacuate.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1162">Foods to Stock at Home and in Your Disaster Supplies Kit.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1163">Even though it is unlikely that an emergency would cut off your food supply for two weeks, consider maintaining a supply in your home that will last that long. The easiest way to develop a two-week stockpile is to increase the amount of basic foods you normally keep on your shelves. Check expiration dates frequently and follow the practice of first-in, first-out.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1164">Pack at least a three-day supply of nonperishable food and water in your Disaster Supplies Kit to be used incase you need to evacuate. Three days worth of supplies should be enough to get you to a location that has additional supplies. This may be outside the impacted area. You need to have these items packed and ready in case there is no time to gather food from the kitchen when disaster strikes. Include both compact, lightweight items like dehydrated foods, which are easy to carry if you must evacuate, and canned foods like fruit, juices, and vegetables that supply a source of water. Choose foods that require no refrigeration, preparation, or cooking. If you must heat food, pack a can of cooking fuel, such as used for camping. Do not pack gasoline, kerosene, or propane.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1165">Familiar foods can lift morale and help people feel secure in time of stress. Try to include foods that everyone will enjoy. Look for foods high in calories, protein, carbohydrates, vitamins, and minerals. Look for canned foods with high liquid content in case water is scarce.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1166">Specifically, consider packing:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1167">Ready-to-eat canned meats, fruits, and vegetables.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1168">Canned juice, milk, and soup.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1169">High-energy foods, such as peanut butter, jelly, salt-free crackers, and energy bars.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1170">Trail mix (prepackaged or homemade).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1171">Comfort foods, such as hard candy, sweetened cereals, candy bars, and cookies.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1172">Instant coffee, tea bags.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1173">Compressed food bars. They store well, are lightweight, taste good, and are nutritious.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1174">Dried foods. They can be nutritious and satisfying, but may contain a lot of salt, which promotes thirst. If salt is a problem, used dried fruit, like raisins.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1175">Freeze-dried foods. They are tasty and lightweight, but will need water for reconstitution.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1176">Whole-grain cereals (oatmeal, granola, multi-grain).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1177">Instant meals. Cups of noodles or cups of soup are a good addition, although they need water for reconstitution and may contain a lot of salt.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1178">Snack-sized canned goods, which generally have pull-top lids or twist-open keys.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1179">Prepackaged beverages. Those in foil packets and foil-lined boxes are sealed and will keep for a long time if the seal is not broken.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1180">Foods for infants, elderly persons, or persons on special diets.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1181">Nonperishable foods for pets and other animals.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1182">When selecting foods, keep in mind that:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1183">Salty foods are usually not a good choice because they will make you thirsty and drinking water may be in short supply.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1184">If your water supply is limited, you should avoid eating foods that are high in fat and protein, even if they are part of your emergency supply, because they require more water for the body to metabolize.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1185">Commercially dehydrated foods often require a lot of water for reconstitution and effort to prepare.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1186">Food packaged in glass bottles and jars is usually heavy and bulky, and the glass can easily break.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1187">Meal-sized canned foods are usually heavy and bulky, but they can be useful because they contain water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1188">Whole grains, beans, and dried pasta require water and cooking time for preparation that could be difficult in a disaster situation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1189">If your electricity goes off and you lose refrigeration:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1190">First, use perishable food from the refrigerator.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1191">Then, use the food from the freezer. To minimize the number of times you open the freezer door, post a list of freezer contents on it. In a well-filled, well-insulated freezer, foods will usually still have ice crystals in their centers (meaning foods are safe to eat) for at least two days.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1192">Finally, begin to use nonperishable foods and staples.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1193">(See Appendix: Keeping Refrigerated Food Safe If the Power Goes Out.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1194">(See Appendix: Food and Water Exposed to Floodwater, Fire, and Chemicals.)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1195">Storing Water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1196">Having an ample supply of clean water is a top priority in an emergency. The following guidelines will help you ensure that members of your household have sufficient water in an emergency situation:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1197">Keep at least a three-day supply of water, that is, a minimum of three gallons per person. It is strongly recommended that you store more if possible. Each person should have one-half gallon per day for drinking and one-half gallon for cooking and sanitation. A normally active person needs to drink at least one-half gallon of water each day. Hot environments and intense physical activity can double that amount. Children, nursing mothers, and ill people will also need more. Be sure to include drinking and clean-up water for your pets. The amount needed will depend on their sizes and the conditions. Remember that pets often drink more water than usual when under stress.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1198">To prepare the safest and most reliable emergency supply of water, purchase commercially bottled water. Keep bottled water in its original container and do not open it until you need to use it.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1199">Store bottled water in the original sealed container and observe the expiration or “use by” date.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1200">If you are preparing your own containers of water, follow the directions below for selecting, cleaning, and filling the containers with water:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1201">Purchase food-grade, water-storage containers from surplus or camping supplies stores to use for water storage.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1202">If you chose to use your own storage containers, chose two-liter, plastic soda bottles—not plastic jugs or cardboard containers that have had milk or fruit juice in them. Milk protein and fruit sugars cannot be adequately removed from these containers and provide an environment for bacterial growth when water is stored in them.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1203">Do not use glass containers because they can break and are heavy.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1204">Do not use cardboard containers, because they can leak easily. These containers are not designed for long-term storage of liquids.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1205">If storing water in plastic soda bottles or food-grade, water-storage containers, follow these steps:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1206">Thoroughly clean them with dishwashing soap and water, and rinse them completely so there is no residual soap.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1207">Sanitize them and their caps by adding a solution of 1 teaspoon of non-scented liquid household chlorine bleach to a quart of water. Swish the sanitizing solution in the containers and caps so that it touches all interior surfaces. After sanitizing the containers and caps, thoroughly rinse out the sanitizing solution with clean water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1208">To fill water containers:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1209">Fill them to the top with regular tap water. If the tap water has been commercially treated from a water utility with chlorine, you do not need to add anything else to the water to keep it clean. If the water you are using comes from a well or water source that is not treated with chlorine, add two drops of non-scented liquid household chlorine bleach to the water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1210">Tightly close the containers using the original caps. Be careful not to contaminate the caps by touching the inside of them with your fingers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1211">Place a date on the outside of the containers so that you know when you filled them. Store them in a cool, dark place.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1212">Replace the water every six months if not using commercially bottled water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1213">Store your three-day supply in a handy place. You need to have water packed and ready in case there is no time to fill water bottles when disaster strikes.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1214">Drinking Water Safety.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1215">Listen to a local radio or television station for announcements from appropriate authorities about the safety of drinking water. Follow their directions.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1216">You can drink water from the community water system unless you have been told or have reason to suspect it has become contaminated.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1217">If the water is contaminated:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1218">Use your emergency supply of water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1219">Purchase bottled water, if necessary, until you are certain that your water supply is safe.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1220">Consider all water from wells, cisterns, and other delivery systems in the disaster area to be unsafe until tested.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1221">Water from melted ice cubes made before the disaster occurred is generally safe to drink.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1222">Water from undamaged hot water tanks and water pipes is generally safe to drink. Turn off the main water valve before draining water from these sources.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1223">Bottled juices and the liquid from canned fruits and vegetables are another source of water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1224">If you need to find drinking water outside your home, you can use rainwater; streams, rivers, and other moving bodies of water; ponds and lakes; and natural springs. If you question its purity, be sure to treat the water first. (See below.) Avoid water with floating material, an odor, or a dark color. Use saltwater only if you distill it first. Do NOT drink floodwater.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1225">Treating Water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1226">Treat water for drinking, cooking, and bathing only if it is of questionable quality. There are several ways to treat water—but none is perfect. Often, the best solution is a combination of methods.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1227">Boiling is the safest method of treating water. Strain water through a clean cloth to remove bulk impurities. Bring water to a rolling boil for about one full minute. Let the water cool before drinking. Boiled water will taste better if you put oxygen back into it by pouring the water back and forth between two clean containers. This will also improve the taste of stored water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1228">Household liquid bleach can kill microorganisms in water. Use chlorine bleach from a freshly opened bottle. Use only regular household liquid bleach that contains approximately 5.25 to 6.0 percent sodium hypochlorite. Do not use scented bleaches, color-safe bleaches, or bleaches with added cleaners. Add 1/8 teaspoon (approximately 0.75 mL or 8 drops) of newly purchased, unscented liquid household bleach per gallon of water. Stir the water well, and let it stand for 30 minutes before you use it. If the water is cloudy or extremely cold, or the bleach label says there is less than 4% sodium hypochlorite in the product, double the amount of bleach you add to the water. Using bleach will not kill parasitic organisms. Other chemicals, such as iodine or water treatment products sold in camping or surplus stores that do not contain 5.25 to 6.0 percent sodium hypochlorite as the only active ingredient, are not recommended and should not be used. Distilling removes salt and other solid impurities from water. Distillation involves boiling water and then collecting the vapor that condenses back to water. The condensed vapor will not include salt or other solid impurities. A relatively simple, although inefficient, way to distill water in an emergency is to suspend a cup over boiling water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1229">(See Appendix: Food and Water Exposed to Floodwater, Fire, and Chemicals.).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1230">Keeping Refrigerated Food Safe if the Power Goes Out.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1231">The loss of power from high wind, fire, flood, or even a traffic accident can be sudden. Without power to run your refrigerator and freezer, the safety of your food could be a concern. Be prepared for an emergency by keeping on hand items that do not require refrigeration, such as shelf-stable food, boxed or canned milk, and canned goods. (See Appendix: Tips for Preparing Your Disaster Supplies Kits.) Make sure you have pre-prepared baby formula for infants, if needed. Remember to use these items in the order you bought them and replace them from time to time.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1232">Knowing ways for keeping food safe when the power goes out will help reduce the worry about what is safe to eat and minimize the potential loss of food. The following information will help you make the right decisions for keeping your family safe:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1233">Always keep your refrigerator at or below 40° F (4° C). Keep your freezer at or below 0° F (-18°C). An appliance thermometer can tell you if your refrigerator and freezer are at the proper temperatures.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1234">If the power goes out, keep the refrigerator and freezer doors closed as much as possible to maintain the cold temperatures. An unopened refrigerator will keep food safely cold for about four hours. A full freezer will stay sufficiently cold for about 48 hours (24 hours if it is half full) if it is unopened.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1235">If your freezer is not full, keep items close together—this helps the food stay cold longer.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1236">Keep frozen meat and poultry items on the lowest (coldest) shelf of the freezer, and separated from other food so that thawing meat or poultry juices will not contaminate the other food.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1237">Obtain dry or block ice to keep your refrigerator as cold as possible if the power is going to be out for a prolonged period of time.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1238">If you are not sure a particular food is cold enough, take its temperature with the food thermometer. Discard any perishable foods (such as meat, poultry, fish, eggs, and leftovers) that have been above 40° F (4° C) for two hours or more, and any food that has an unusual odor, color, or texture, or feels warm to the touch.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1239">Be sure to discard any fully cooked items in either the freezer or the refrigerator that have come in contact with raw meat juices.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1240">Remember, you cannot rely solely on appearance or odor. Never taste food to determine its safety. Some foods may look and smell fine, but if they have been at room temperature too long, bacteria that cause food-borne illness can begin to grow very rapidly. Some types of bacteria produce toxins that are not destroyed by cooking.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1241">If previously frozen food is partially or completely thawed when the power comes back on:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1242">You can safely refreeze it if it contains ice crystals or is at 40° F (4° C) or below. You will have to evaluate each item separately.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1243">Partially thawed food can be refrozen safely, but refreezing may reduce the quality of some food.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1244">Raw meats and poultry from the freezer can be refrozen without too much quality loss.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1245">Prepared food, vegetables, and fruits can be refrozen, but there may be some quality loss.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1246">Fruit juices can be refrozen safely without much quality loss, but frozen fruit will become mushy.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1247">Food from the refrigerator and freezer are not safe outdoors, even in cold weather or snow because:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1248">Frozen food can thaw if it is exposed to the sun's rays.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1249">Refrigerated food may become too warm and food-borne bacteria could grow.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1250">The outdoor temperature could vary hour by hour, and the temperature outdoors would not be satisfactory to protect both refrigerated and frozen foods at the same time. For example, if the outdoor temperature is 25° F (-4° C), it is too cold for refrigerated food and too warm for frozen food.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1251">Perishable items would be exposed to unsanitary conditions and to animals that may be attracted to the food. Animals are not clean and may harbor disease. Never use food that has come in contact with an animal.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1252">Instead of putting food outdoors, consider taking advantage of the cold by making ice. Fill buckets, empty milk cartons, or cans with water and leave them outside to freeze. Then put the homemade ice in your refrigerator and freezer or coolers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1253">Food and Water Exposed to Floodwater, Fire, and Chemicals.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1254">After a flood, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1255">Wear gloves, boots, and a long-sleeved shirt and long pants when cleaning up.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1256">Discard all food or drinking water that came in contact with floodwater, including canned goods. It is impossible to know if containers were damaged and the seal compromised.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1257">Discard wooden spoons and cutting boards, plastic utensils, and baby bottle nipples and pacifiers if they have been covered by floodwater. There is no way to safely clean them.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1258">Thoroughly wash metal pans, ceramic dishes and utensils that have been covered by floodwater with hot soapy water and sanitize them by boiling them in clean or properly treated water or by immersing them for 15 minutes in a solution of 1 teaspoon of chlorine bleach per quart of water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1259">Consider what you can do ahead of time to keep your food safe in an emergency. For example, if you live in a location that could be affected by a flood, plan your food storage so that your appliances and food shelves will be safely out of the way of floodwater. And remember to store pet food where it will be safe from possible contamination by floodwater.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1260">After a fire, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1261">Throw out food and water exposed to fire because they may have been damaged by the heat, smoke, and fumes of the fire and by the chemicals used to fight the fire.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1262">Throw out food and water in cans or jars even if they appear to be undamaged, because the heat from a fire can activate spoilage bacteria and make the food and water unsafe.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1263">Throw out any raw food or food in permeable packaging—cardboard, plastic wrap, screw-topped jars and bottles, etc., even if it was stored in the refrigerator.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1264">Throw out any food that has an off-flavor or odor when it is prepared.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1265">Toxic gases released from burning materials are very dangerous. These gases can kill; they can also contaminate food and water. Food and water stored in refrigerators or freezers can also become contaminated by gases. The refrigerator seal is not airtight and gases can get inside.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1266">If food or water has been exposed to toxic chemicals, throw it away. The chemicals cannot be washed off the food. This includes food stored at room temperature, such as fruits and vegetables, as well as food in permeable containers like cardboard and screw-topped jars and bottles, even if it is in the refrigerator. Canned goods are the only foods that can be safely kept after exposure to chemicals and then only if the unopened cans are washed with a dishwashing detergent and then immersed in a bleach solution (1 teaspoon of bleach per quart of water).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1267">If cookware and utensils have been exposed to toxic chemicals, wash them with dishwashing detergent and then immerse them in a bleach solution (1 teaspoon of bleach per quart of water).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1268">What to Do if Evacuation Is Necessary Because of a Storm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1269">If you are advised to evacuate or if you think it is appropriate to evacuate, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1270">Leave as soon as possible, preferably in daylight. Avoid flooded roads and watch for washed-out bridges. Evacuation will probably take longer than expected. Give yourself plenty of time.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1271">Secure your home by unplugging appliances and turning off the electricity and the main water valve. This will reduce potential damage to your appliances from power surges and to your home.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1272">Tell someone outside the storm area where you are going—(the out-of-town contact you identified in your Family Disaster Plan). Relatives and friends will be concerned about your safety. Letting someone know your travel plans will help relieve their fear and anxiety.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1273">If time permits and you live in an identified surge zone or area prone to flooding, move furniture to a higher floor. Moving valuable furnishings helps reduce the potential for damage.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1274">Bring your Disaster Supplies Kit, including warm protective clothing. People frequently arrive at shelters or hotels with nothing. Having these items with you will make you more comfortable. While shelters provide a safe place to stay and food, specialty items for infants and individuals on restricted diets may not be available. It may be several days before permission is given by local authorities to reenter an evacuated area.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1275">Lock your home and leave. There may be individuals evacuating after you, or returning before you. Police may be busy with storm-related emergencies and not able to patrol neighborhoods as usual.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1276">What to Do When There Is Flooding.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1277">If you are outdoors, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1278">Stay out of areas subject to flooding. Dips, low spots, canyons, washes, etc. can become filled with water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1279">Climb to high ground and stay there. Move away from dangerous floodwater.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1280">If you come upon a flowing stream where water is above your ankles, stop, turn around, and go another way. Never try to walk, swim, or drive through swift water. Many flood fatalities are caused by people attempting to drive through water, or people playing in high water. If it is moving swiftly, even water six inches (15 centimeters) deep can sweep you off your feet.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1281">If you are driving, you should:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1282">Avoid already flooded areas and areas subject to sudden flooding. Do not attempt to cross flowing streams. Many flood fatalities are caused by people attempting to drive through water or by people playing in high water. The depth of water is not always obvious. The roadbed may be washed out under the water, and you could be stranded or trapped. Also, standing water may be electrically charged from underground or downed power lines. Rapidly rising water may stall he engine, engulf the vehicle and its occupants, and sweep them away. Look out for flooding at highway dips, bridges, and low areas. As little as six inches of water may cause you to lose control of your vehicle and two feet (0.6 meters) of water will carry away most vehicles, including SUVs and pickup trucks.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1283">Stay away from underpasses. Underpasses can fill rapidly with water, while the adjacent roadway remains clear. Driving into an underpass can quickly put you in five to six feet (1.5 to 1.8 meters) of water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1284">Turn around and find another route if you come upon rapidly rising water. Move to higher ground away from rivers, streams, creeks, and storm drains. If your route is blocked by floodwater or barricades, find another route. Barricades are put up by local officials to protect people from unsafe roads. Driving around them can be a serious risk.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1285">“Wind Safe” Room.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1286">A "wind safe” room is a reinforced area of a home designed to withstand severe windstorms. While basements offer some protection from damaging winds, the level of protection can be increased greatly by building a reinforced shelter area in a basement, or constructing a shelter in an above-ground room such as an interior closet or a small study room.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1287">An effective “wind safe” room must be strong enough to survive extreme wind speeds and the impact of airborne debris, sufficiently affordable to appeal to homeowners, and accessible quickly in the event a severe storm approaches. “Wind safe” rooms are easiest to install when a home is being built; however, they can also be added to many existing homes. A variety of options exists for homes with basements, homes built on a "slab-on-grade" foundation, and homes with a "crawlspace" foundation. Typical costs range from $2,000 for a simple "lean-to" shelter in a new-home basement, to $6,000 or more for an above-ground, steel-sheathing shelter.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1288">Get more information from the Federal Emergency Management Agency (FEMA) about building a “wind safe” room. Also for more information, check out the Institute for</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1289">Business and Home Safety at www.ibhs.org.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1290">Detailed construction plans and information related to safe rooms can be found at http://www.fema.gov/mit/saferoom/.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1291">Emergency Sanitation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1292">In many shelters during an emergency, people will need to use improvised, emergency toilets if the water supply has been cut off. These kinds of toilets consist of any watertight container with a snug-fitting cover.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1293">Use a garbage container, pail, or bucket.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1294">If the container is small, keep a large container (also with a cover) available for waste disposal.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1295">If possible, line both containers with plastic bags.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1296">Every time the emergency toilet is used, pour or sprinkle a small amount of regular household disinfectant, such as creosol or chlorine bleach, into the container to reduce odors and germs.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1297">After each use, replace the lid.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1298">Frostbite and Hypothermia.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1299">Frostbite and hypothermia are cold-related emergencies that may quickly become life or limb threatening. Preventing cold-related emergencies includes not starting an activity in, on, or around cold water unless you know you can get help quickly in an emergency. Be aware of the wind chill. Dress appropriately and avoid staying in the cold too long. Wear a hat and gloves when appropriate with layers of clothing. Drink plenty of warm fluids or warm water but avoid caffeine and alcohol. Stay active to maintain body heat. Take frequent breaks from the cold. Avoid unnecessary exposure of any part of the body to the cold. Get out of the cold immediately if the signals of hypothermia or frostbite appear.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1300">Frostbite is the freezing of a specific body part such as fingers, toes, the nose or earlobes.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1301">Signals of frostbite include: lack of feeling in the affected area; skin that appears waxy, is cold to the touch, or is discolored (flushed, white or gray, yellow or blue).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1302">What to do for frostbite:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1303">1. Move the person to a warm place.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1304">2. Handle the area gently; never rub the affected area.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1305">3. Warm gently by soaking the affected area in warm water (100–105 degrees F) until it appears red and feels warm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1306">4. Loosely bandage the area with dry, sterile dressings.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1307">5. If the person’s fingers or toes are frostbitten, place dry, sterile gauze between them to keep them separated.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1308">6. Avoid breaking any blisters.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1309">7. do not allow the affected area to refreeze.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1310">8. Seek professional medical care as soon as possible.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1311">Hypothermia is another cold-related emergencies. Hypothermia may quickly become life threatening. Hypothermia is caused by the cooling of the body caused by the failure of the body’s warming system. The goals of first aid are to restore normal body temperature and to care for any conditions while waiting for EMS personnel.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1312">Signals of hypothermia include: shivering, numbness, glassy stare; apathy, weakness, impaired judgment; loss of consciousness.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1313">What to do for hypothermi:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1314">1. CALL 9-1-1 or the local emergency number.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1315">2. Gently move the person to a warm place.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1316">3. Monitor breathing and circulation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1317">4. Give rescue breathing and CPR if needed.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1318">5. Remove any wet clothing and dry the person.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1319">6. Warm the person slowly by wrapping in blankets or by putting dry clothing on the person. Hot water bottles and chemical hot packs may be used when first wrapped in a towel or blanket before applying. Do not warm the person too quickly, such as by immersing him or her in warm water. Rapid warming may cause dangerous heart arrhythmias. warm the core first (trunk, abdomen), not the extremities (hands, feet). This is important to mention because most people will try to warm hands and feet first and that can cause shock.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1320">First Aid Kit for Pets.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1321">A fully equipped household first aid kit contains almost all of the supplies you may need for your pets. A simple first aid kit for your pets should include these additional items in a waterproof container:</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1322">Latex (or hypoallergenic material) gloves</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1323">Gauze sponges ( a variety of sizes)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1324">Gauze roll, 2-inch width</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1325">Elastic cling bandage</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1326">Material to make a splint</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1327">Adhesive tape, hypoallergenic</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1328">Non-adherent sterile pads</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1329">Small scissors</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1330">Tweezers</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1331">Magnifying glass</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1332">Grooming clippers or safety razor</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1333">Nylon leash</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1334">Towel</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1335">Muzzle</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1336">Compact emergency “blanket” (available in the camping department of many stores)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1337">Water-based sterile lubricant</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1338">Hydrogen peroxide (3 percent)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1339">Rubbing alcohol;</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1340">Topical antibiotic ointment</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1341">Antiseptic towelettes</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1342">Insect sting stop pads</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1343">Cotton-tipped swabs</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1344">Instant cold pack</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1345">Epsom salts</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1346">Baby-dose syringe or eye dropper</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1347">Sterile eye lubricant</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1348">Sterile saline wash</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1349">Safety pins (medium size 4)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1350">Tongue depressors</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1351">Diphenhydramine, if approved by your veterinarian</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1352">Glucose paste or syrup</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1353">Styptic powder or pencil</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1354">Plastic card (such as old credit card) to scrape away stingers</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1355">List of emergency phone numbers including those for your pet’s veterinarian, an after-hours emergency veterinary hospital, and the National Animal Poison Control Center (1-888-426-4435) and money to make a phone call.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1356">Petroleum jelly</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1357">Penlight with batteries (AA)</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1358">Clean cloth</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1359">Needle-nose pliers</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1360">For a complete list of items for your pet first aid kit and detailed information on how to provide first aid for your pets, consult Pet First Aid by Barbara Mammato, DVM, MPH, a handbook sponsored by the American Red Cross and The Humane Society of the United States.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1361">What to Do if Evacuation Is Necessary Because of a Storm.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1362">What to Do When There Is Flooding.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1363">“Wind Safe” Room.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1364">Emergency Sanitation.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1365">Portable Generators.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1366">Smoke Alarms.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1367">Carbon Monoxide Alarms.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1368">Fire Extinguishers.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1369">Home Fire Sprinkler Systems.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1370">Arc-Fault Circuit Interrupters (AFCIs).</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1371">Electrical Hazards.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1372">Fire Hazards.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1373">Frostbite and Hypothermia.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1374">First Aid Kit Contents.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1375">First Aid Kit for Pets.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1376">Foods to Stock at Home and in Your Disaster Supplies Kit.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1377">Tips for Preparing Your Disaster Supplies Kits.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1378">Keeping Refrigerated Food Safe if the Power Goes Out.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1379">Food and Water Exposed to Floodwater, Fire, and Chemicals.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1380">Treating Water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1381">Storing Water.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1382">Drinking Water Safety.</bu>
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_1383">Emergency Supplies for Your Vehicle.</bu>
</cl>
<cl na="Mine" xid="id_10002">
<bu cl="txt" xid="id_11112">Create and/or drag/drop your own bullets here,e.g. drag bullets from the LowerTopClip to the UpperTopClip (in this case you must first "unhide"  (i.e. "show") the LowerTopClip, in Screen 1).</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11122">
<a id="id_11122" rel="external" href="01s_sprain.mp4">*Sprains and strains (British Red Cross mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11123">
<a id="id_11123" rel="external" href="02s_choking.mp4">*Chocking (British Red Cross, mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11124">
<a id="id_11124" rel="external" href="04s_adult_cpr.mp4">*Adult CPR (British Red Cross, mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11125">
<a id="id_11125" rel="external" href="05s_child_cpr.mp4">*Child CPR (British Red Cross, mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11126">
<a id="id_11126" rel="external" href="06s_baby_cpr.mp4">*Baby CPR (British Red Cross, mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11127">
<a id="id_11127" rel="external" href="07s_bleeding_hand.mp4">*Bleeding hand (British Red Cross, mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11128">
<a id="id_11128" rel="external" href="09s_burns.mp4">*Burns and scalds (British Red Cross, mp4)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11130">
<a id="id_11130" rel="external" href="ALS-DisasterPreparedness-020712.mp3">*ALS Disaster Preparedness 02-07-2012 (archive.org, mp3)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11131">
<a id="id_11131" rel="external" href="City-to-cityRespondingAndPartneringInDisaster.mp3">*City-to-city Responding And Partnering In Disaster (archive.org, mp3)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11133">
<a id="id_11133" rel="external" href="Diagram_of_the_human_heart.png">Diagram of the human heart (wikipedia.org, png)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11134">
<a id="id_11134" rel="external" href="Direct-pressure-and-elevation.jpg">Direct pressure and elevation (wikipedia.org, jpg)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11135">
<a id="id_11135" rel="external" href="Forearm_splint.jpg">Forearm splint (wikipedia.org, jpg)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11136">
<a id="id_11136" rel="external" href="Gray507.png">Head blood vessels-[Gray507] (wikipedia.org, png)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11137">
<a id="id_11137" rel="external" href="Tongue-blocking-airways.png">Tongue blocking airways (wikipedia.org, png)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11154">
<a id="id_11154" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?City=New+Orleans&amp;_id=Tj_1Ypox3RGtgHFNYEsBXw&amp;_render=json&amp;radius=67 National Hurricane Center Advisories: http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=7PptTnpE3RGSPAlJJhOy0Q&amp;_render=json">Hurricane (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11155">
<a id="id_11155" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?City=New+Orleans&amp;_id=Tj_1Ypox3RGtgHFNYEsBXw&amp;_render=json&amp;radius=67 National Hurricane Center Advisories: http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=7PptTnpE3RGSPAlJJhOy0Q&amp;_render=json">Sea State Watcher(!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11156">
<a id="id_11156" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=6632151702a89b12a40f71ce24005553&amp;_render=json">Hurricane Tracker(!Yahoo Pipes, json) </a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11157">
<a id="id_11157" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=7PptTnpE3RGSPAlJJhOy0Q&amp;_render=json">National Hurricane Center Advisories (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11158">
<a id="id_11158" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=eA87isVd3hGw_Zx_U5Wufg&amp;_render=json">SPC Storm Reports (Yesterday) (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11159">
<a id="id_11159" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=6632151702a89b12a40f71ce24005553&amp;_render=json">Current Tropical Storms (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11160">
<a id="id_11160" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=TJ_Ru7zH3RG0l1qx_w6H4A&amp;_render=json">Today's Storm Reports (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11161">
<a id="id_11161" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?State=WI&amp;_id=Sk81h4cH3RGl44WkJZhxuA&amp;_render=json">National Severe Thunderstorm Warnings (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11162">
<a id="id_11122" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=xL2ZsmPI2xGZEhiNkAtvUw&amp;_render=json">Wildfire News (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11163">
<a id="id_11163" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=Tm1_uDyI3BGAPm8b2h2EvQ&amp;_render=json">Earthquakes in Northern California (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11164">
<a id="id_11164" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=7250d674dbac23b66f3f25a2c55d9ea7&amp;_render=json">National Weather Service Observed River Conditions and River Condition Alerts - Red River of the North Main Stem (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11165">
<a id="id_11165" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=BjgSJBEP3RG0ghcAOTY80A&amp;_render=json">North Dakota Water, Weather, and Natural Resource News (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11166">
<a id="id_11166" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=aEuinrS03BGmjFiQEpPZnA&amp;_render=json&amp;magnitudeThreshold=1 ">Quakescope (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11167">
<a id="id_11167" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=5f54b30d36a9eacff1a88669ca03aaa8&amp;_render=json">world earthquake map (past 7 days) (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11168">
<a id="id_11168" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=VEm5_4253BGSBceQJphxuA&amp;_render=json&amp;filterCriteria1=flood&amp;zoneCode=TXZ16">Weather alert (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11169">
<a id="id_11169" rel="external" href="http://pipes.yahoo.com/pipes/pipe.run?_id=vkbigS9w3BGFQgxmLe2fWQ&amp;_render=json">FEMA Regional News (!Yahoo Pipes, json)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11172">
<a id="id_11172" rel="external" href="Anchor_Fuel_Tanks_2-[how2005].epub">**Anchor Fuel Tanks 2-[how2005] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11173">
<a id="id_11173" rel="external" href="Add_Waterproof_Veneer_to_Exterior_Walls_2-[how2003].epub">**Add Waterproof Veneer to Exterior Walls 2-[how2003](Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11174">
<a id="id_11174" rel="external" href="Raise_Electrical_System_Components_2-[how2004].epub">**Raise Electrical System Components 2-[how2004] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11175">
<a id="id_11175" rel="external" href="Raise_or_Floodproof_HVAC _quipment_2-[how2006].epub">**Raise or Floodproof HVAC  equipment 2-[how2006] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11176">
<a id="id_11176" rel="external" href="Install_Sewer_Backflow_Valves_2-[how2007].epub">**Install Sewer Backflow Valves 2-[how2007] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11177">
<a id="id_11177" rel="external" href="Reinforce_or_Replace_Garage_Doors_2-[how2016].epub">**Reinforce or Replace Garage Doors 2-[how2016] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11178">
<a id="id_11178" rel="external" href="Protecting_Your_Property_From_Wind_2-[how2017].epub">**Protecting Your Property From Wind 2-[how2017] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11179">
<a id="id_11179" rel="external" href="Remove_Trees_and_Potential_Windborne_Missiles_2-[how2020].epub">**Remove Trees and Potential Windborne Missiles 2-[how2020] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11180">
<a id="id_11180" rel="external" href="Protecting_Your_Business_From_Disaster_2-[how2021].epub">**Protecting Your Business From Disaster 2-[how2021] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11181">
<a id="id_11181" rel="external" href="Protecting_Your_Business_From_Earthquakes-[how2023].epub">**Protecting Your Business From Earthquakes-[how2023] (Fema, epub)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11182">
<a id="id_11182" rel="external" href="01s_sprain.ogv">*Sprains and strains (British Red Cross ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11183">
<a id="id_11183" rel="external" href="02s_choking.ogv">*Chocking (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11184">
<a id="id_11184" rel="external" href="04s_adult_cpr.ogv">*Adult CPR (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11185">
<a id="id_11185" rel="external" href="05s_child_cpr.ogv">*Child CPR (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11186">
<a id="id_11186" rel="external" href="06s_baby_cpr.ogv">*Baby CPR (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11187">
<a id="id_11187" rel="external" href="07s_bleeding_hand.ogv">*Bleeding hand (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11188">
<a id="id_11188" rel="external" href="07s_bleeding_hand.ogv">*Bleeding hand (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11189">
<a id="id_11189" rel="external" href="09s_burns.ogv">*Burns and scalds (British Red Cross, ogv)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11190">
<a id="id_11190" rel="external" href="ALS-DisasterPreparedness-020712.ogg">*ALS Disaster Preparedness 02-07-2012 (archive.org, ogg)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11191">
<a id="id_11191" rel="external" href="City-to-cityRespondingAndPartneringInDisaster.ogg">*City-to-city Responding And Partnering In Disaster (archive.org, ogg)</a>
</bu>
<bu xid="id_11193">In this clip are the CJE docs. It is now all in one file, but it will be split out in multiple files or (better) "accordionized", be made more comprehensible for the novice and generally improved.</bu>
<bu xid="id_11194">README 1st: The first bullet (actually a sub-clip)  contains streaming video from Youtube. 
On Android the native Android Video- player gave best result. Others might show erratic behavior. You might try out which video-player gives decent results. 
The video's in the last 2 Clip-bullets can only be viewed when you have an on-board server The video must first be downloaded from Dropbox at http://db.tt/edEJFi4y and must be dropped in the web-document-root (: the same place where all the cje-files reside).
These video's were found somewhere in the past and I  couldn't found them anymore so I placed them for download here at Dropbox, but all credits go to the British Red Cross at www.redcross.org.uk. There is NOT ANY affiliation between Calamity Jane Express ® and the British Red Cross.</bu>
<bu xid="id_11195">README 1st: Here are some examples of podcast-streams found on archive.org.
Bullets with a *-mark can only be played when you have the developers version and a local on-board server. The video's can then be downloaded from archive.com with the same titles as given in the bullet-name or one can do a search on "disaster".
situation were the only way to return is the browsers Back-button, after you listened to the podcast. </bu>
<bu xid="id_11196">README 1st: Here are some pics from wikipedia.org that must be download from Dropbox at http://db.tt/CcYFzgDe, so that it can be viewed(in png and jpg format).</bu>
<bu xid="id_11198">README 1st: These are so-calledYahoo Pipes in which data that might come from different sites canbe filtered, added, grouped, sorted etc before they are output in some format and, if needed, further processed by the user. Here the output is in json format for further processing. If you want to do it yourself, please see bullet "Learn more about Yahoo Pipes and rss".
Actually it's a way of providing external/remote functionality: if you don't have the functionality on-board, than it can be "outsourced" to an external source and you get only the result back to you.</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11199">
<a id="id_11199" rel="external" href="http://fastwonderblog.com/yahoo-pipes-and-rss-hacks/">
Learn more about Yahoo Pipes and RSS (fastwonderblog.com)
</a>
</bu>
<bu xid="id_11200">README 1st: These are files from FEMA in epub format so that you can read it with special e-reader software. The **-marks mean that of this moment it can only be viewed if you simulate this whole web-app on a desktop/laptop. On a smartphone/tablet it will show you garbled data because the epub format will not automatically fire up an e-reader app. In future versions it should also be possible to start ANY native app and/or open ANY filetype from this "bui" (:bulleted-user-interface), so that EVERYTHING can be opened/started from here.
The files are from Fema and are only converted here, at my site into epub-format, to make it readable with an e-reader hardware/software.
Credits go to Fema at www.fema.gov. There is NOT ANY affiliation between Calamity Jane Express ® and Fema.</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11201">
<a id="id_11201" rel="external" href="index2.html">
CJE technical documentation in 1 file. Once the file is loaded, tap on a subject to see its content (subjects are  grouped "accordionized"). Tap Back-button of browser to return.
</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11202">
<a id="id_11202" rel="external" href="cjeman.html">CJE Manual (to be improved for the novice).</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11203">
<a id="id_11203" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1qje-XlNowI">Heart attack  (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11204">
<a id="id_11204" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BQ_62avLPv0">Unconscious and not breathing (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11205">
<a id="id_11205" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=HzFD6dcNvH8">Unconscious and breathing (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11206">
<a id="id_11206" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=PCNTMIcOMpE">Stroke (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11207">
<a id="id_11207" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7MPJauo4DdY">Seizure (epilepsy) (British Red cross, steraming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11208">
<a id="id_11208" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OqDdLUi7kkA">Head injury  (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11209">
<a id="id_11209" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=1Ceh9CWHS7k">Asthma (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11210">
<a id="id_11210" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L4o6D10AkMg">Poison and harmful substances (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11211">
<a id="id_11211" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=fuHg7cx-r3g">Distress (British Red Cross, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11215">
<a id="id_11215" rel="external" href="http://archive.org/download/DisasterPreparedness/ALS-DisasterPreparedness-020712.mp3">ALS-DisasterPreparedness-020712 (archive.org, streaming/mp3)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11216">
<a id="id_11216" rel="external" href="http://archive.org/download/DisasterPreparedness/ALS-DisasterPreparedness-020712.ogg">ALS-DisasterPreparedness-020712 (archive.org, streaming/ogg)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11217">
<a id="id_11217" rel="external" href="http://archive.org/download/City-to-cityRespondingAndPartneringInDisaster/City-to-cityRespondingAndPartneringInDisaster.mp3">City-to-City Responding and Partnering in Disaster (archive.org, streaming/mp3)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11218">
<a id="id_11218" rel="external" href="http://archive.org/download/City-to-cityRespondingAndPartneringInDisaster/City-to-cityRespondingAndPartneringInDisaster.ogg">City-to-City Responding and Partnering in Disaster (archive.org, streaming/ogg)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11233">
<a id="id_11233" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=eJnUzsTz3OA&amp;fmt=18">Sort functions (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11234">
<a id="id_11234" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7-OKTWrVh6I&amp;fmt=18">Scroll and tap to view content (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11235">
<a id="id_11235" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k-XNIUsaw0g&amp;fmt=18">Search by traversal/enumeration (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11236">
<a id="id_11236" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0YRs9Nra3FU&amp;fmt=18">Delete via Temporaries (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11237">
<a id="id_11237" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=8V5wdtOeXx8&amp;fmt=18">Scroll and tap to view content (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11238">
<a id="id_11238" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VPqpqbISFWs&amp;fmt=18">Hide UpperTopClip/Search through LowerTopClip(Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11239">
<a id="id_11239" rel="external" href="http://i2.ytimg.com/vi/E6-6A830sk4/mqdefault.jpg&amp;fmt=18">Enable various selctions (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11240">
<a id="id_11240" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YSd7-wsjfDE&amp;fmt=18">Drag from LowerTopClip to UpperTopClip (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11241">
<a id="id_11241" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=XEHwLTPx_Wg&amp;fmt=18">Drag/drop within Temporaries (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11242">
<a id="id_11242" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OxzAoJPn_Yk&amp;fmt=18">Delete (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11243">
<a id="id_11243" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Cf9xCJ-CD6A|fmt=18">Createclip and traverse (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11244">
<a id="id_11244" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=JzNR0SX4-5A&amp;fmt=18">Create bullet + hyperlink (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11245">
<a id="id_11245" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=w3NdI5aCsiM&amp;fmt=18">Create/change bullet + hyperlink (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu cl="lnk" xid="id_11246">
<a id="id_11246" rel="external" href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=afSWkQuNbLY&amp;fmt=18">Add video (CJE: Youtube, streaming)</a>
</bu>
<bu xid="id_11248">Here you read the latest news or "must read" tips before you start (e.g. for the first time), to get the best experience.
For example that the best and smooth behavior (on my mobile Samsung GS2 plus Android 2.3.6) came surprisingly from a mobile-browser outsider: Dolphin (dolphin.com). Other mobile browsers gave (unfortunately and unexpected actually) erratic behavior especially during drag/drop (Firefox Mobile) in combination with scrolling (Opera Mobile), but hopefully that will be solved in future versions. Other well known mobile browsers couldn't be tested because they couldn't be installed on my mobile Samsung GS2, like Chrome, Safari Mobile and Windows Mobile. But might  you have other experiences, then the please let me know.
You must also use CJE's own "back" button as much as possible, because the historical track of CJE and that of your browser are different. The only combinations that did things smooth and right all the time were, like said, Dolphin Mobile browser in combination with Androids native Videos-player (if watching videos), at least on my Samsung GS2 with Android 2.3.6. But expect things to improve in future versions... (?)</bu>
</cl>
</root>